<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnreasonablenesse of the separation Made apparant, by an examination of Mr. Iohnsons pretended reasons, published an. 1608. Wherby hee laboureth to iustifie his schisme from the church assemblies of England.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113892</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849121</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849121</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 779:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnreasonablenesse of the separation Made apparant, by an examination of Mr. Iohnsons pretended reasons, published an. 1608. Wherby hee laboureth to iustifie his schisme from the church assemblies of England.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
                  <author>Ames, William, 1576-1633. Manudicition for Mr. Robinson.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Waters,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Dort :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw. Includes: Ames, William. A manudiction for Mr. Robinson.</note>
                  <note>"The unreasonablenesse of the separation" answers STC 14660: Francis Johnson's "Certayne reasons and arguments proving that it is not lawfull to heare the present ministerie of the Church of England". "A manudiction for Mr. Robinson" answers: John Robinson's "Of religious communion private, &amp; publique" (stc 21115)--Folger Shakespeare Library catalogue.</note>
                  <note>"The unreasonableness of the separation" has anonymous preface, identified as by William Ames in STC 3533. "A manudicition for Mr. Robinson" is answered by STC 21111--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-Q⁴ (A1 blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks(?) all after P3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, Francis, 1562-1618. --  Certayne reasons and arguments.</term>
               <term>Robinson, John, 1575?-1625. --  Manumission to a manuduction.</term>
               <term>Robinson, John, 1575?-1625. --  Of religious communion private, &amp; publique.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNREASONABLENESSE <hi>of the ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Made apparant, by an examination of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iohnſons pretended reaſons, publiſhed an. 1608. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee laboureth to iuſtifie his ſchisme from the Church Aſſemblies of England.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Tim 1.5.6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The end of the commandement is charitie, out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of fayth vnfayned. From which ſome hauing ſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, haue turned a ſide vnto vaine Jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, deſiring to bee teachers of the Law, vnderſtanding neither what they ſay, nor wherof they affirme.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT DORT,</hi> Printed by George Waters. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WELL meaning Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hink not euill, if thou meaneſt well, wee intend not to inſult over him that is downe, or to purſue a man that is flying of himſelfe: but to lend him a hand that knoweth not well which way to take. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iohnſon in deed, is rather to bee pitied, then much oppoſed: wee need but ſtand ſtill as lookers on: hee falleth willingly on his owne ſword but that his fall may bee a riſing againe, not onely to himſelf, but to others alſo, both armour-bearers &amp; followers of his: it was iudged neceſſarie, to guide them a litle while their heads are dizzy, &amp; bring them fairly from of the bogge they haue ſtood on.</p>
            <p>It is not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Johnſon that is dealt with alone
<pb facs="tcp:177068:3"/>for change the name onely, and put in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, or any ſuch: themſelues will not ſay but the reaſons are theirs, and the anſwer, to them, as well as to him. Jt may bee that they hauing leſſe acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with logicall formes of diſpute, will looke for large diſcourſe, or heaped quotations out of ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But reaſon will tell them, that many words doe rather hide them vntie the knot of a ſyllogiſme: and much quoting may proue ſome-thing, but anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wereth not directly to any thing. Now the wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters meaning was, not to gather proofes, but to poynt at the weakneſſe of ſuch as theſe men haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. Read therfore with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and learn a mean betwixt <hi>All</hi> and <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:3"/>
            <head>THE MAINE <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Johnſons Reaſons,</hi> as it is propounded by himſelf, is this, <hi>That it is not lawfull to heare or haue any ſpiritual communion wit the preſent Miniſtery of the Church, Aſſemblies of Englande.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich hee laboureth to proue. 1. By Reaſons (as hee fancieth) drawne from Scripture, and other Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Argumentes collected from the writeinges of them, whom hee ſtileth (in diſdaine) forward Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. And this hee performeth as far as the remainders of his logick skill will giue him leaue, in moode and figure. But the figure for the moſte part is of his owne ſhapeing, ſuch as neuer came forth of any logick Schooles: yet feing the truth hee oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth receaueth noe diſadvantage therby. I can (for my owne parte) be content that his Syllogiſmes ſtil retaine thoſe formes and figures, that hee hath put vpon them, and ſpare the labour of Tranſlating them into nue. And ſo without any further expence of wordes, I come to the Examination of the firſt ſort of Reaſons.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:177068:4"/>
               <head>THE FIRST SORTE OF Reaſons from the Scriptures and other Teſtimonies Examined.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The firſt Reaſon Examined.</head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>All are bound in the worſhip of God to heare and communicate onely with that ministery which Christ hath giuen, and ſet in his Church for that worke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the preſent Ministery of the Church Aſſemblies of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, is not that which Christ hath giuen, and ſet in his Church for the worke of his Ministery.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is not lawfull for any in the worſhip of God to heare or communicate with the preſent Ministery of the Church Aſſemblies of England.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Not to contend about the Propoſition. I deny the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: and affirme, That the preſent Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies (how ſoever it may in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler parts of the execution, happely be defectiue in ſome places) is, (for the ſubſtance thereof) that very ſame Miniſtery which Chriſt hath ſet in his Church for the worke of his miniſtery whether it bee the miniſtery of thoſe which hee calleth the forward Preachers, or of thoſe which being qualified according to the true inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the lawe, do ſubſcribe, and conforme according to the laws of the State.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:4"/>
                     <head>Fr. Ihon.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Ministery which Christ hath giuen, and ſet in his Church, is, of Apostles, Prophets, Euangelists, Pastors, and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.12.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the preſent Ministery of the Church of England is none of theſe ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.12.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therefore it is not the Miniſtery which Christ hath giuen and ſet in his Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The preſent Miniſtery of the Church of England (1. of the Church Aſſemblies of England) is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The preſent Miniſtery of the Church of England is of Prelates, Priestes and Deacons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But nether Prelates, Prieſtes, nor Deacons of that Church, are Pastors or Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.12.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therefore it is none of thoſe ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.12.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>I denye both Prepoſition and Aſſumption. For 1. Though our Preletes, doe ſometimes voluntarily and occaſionnally performe the ſame worke and ſeruice in ſome of our Church Aſſemblies, which our ordinary Miniſters doe, yet their Prelaticall or Epiſcopall office or Miniſtery is not the proper Miniſtery of any of our Church Aſſemblies. But (in the intent of our lawes) their propre Miniſtery conſiſts in overſeeing the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:5"/> 2. Though ſometimes our Miniſters be called PRIESTS and DEACONS yet the MINISTERY vnder thoſe names aſſigned vnto them, and which they exerciſe is not the proper and eſſentiall Miniſtery of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſtes or Deacons; but of Paſtors and Teachers: Soe that they are onely in aequivocation, and name, or Metaphorically Prieſtes and Deacons: But really Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers, and therfore ſuch Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, may bee, and indeede and truth are ſuch Paſtors and Teachers as are ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Prepoſition is manifest.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. The Law of that Church admitteth not any other Miniſtery, but that of their Prelacie Priesthoode and Deaconry, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued amongst them ſelues or from the Papistes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. Their Conſtitution is ſuch as all the Miniſters of that Church must bee Priests or Deacons, and theiſe alſo either in a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior degree as the Prelates, Arch. Biſhops Suffraganes &amp;c. or in an inferior, as Parſons, Vicars, Stipendaries, Chaplins.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. It is not neceſſary that the Miniſtery of a contrey or nation ſhould be alwaies ſuch as the law eſtabliſheth or admitteth: The Miniſtery (at leaſt in ſome places) may be good though the law in generall ſhould admit and eſtabliſhe ſuch a one as is bad: as on the contrarye ſide, the miniſtery may at ſome times, and in ſome caſes be bad, though the laws admit, &amp; eſtabliſh neuer ſoe good; for the Gouernors of Churches and common wealths who haue the diſpenſation of lawes, may in their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian wiſedome, and moderation permitt a miniſtery in
<pb facs="tcp:177068:5"/>ſundrie reſpects different from that which the laws re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; yea and our owne Gouernors in fact haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the miniſtery of ſome, who neuer receiued ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, either from Papiſts or themſelues. And hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant but that ſome by connivencie are yet ſuffred in ſome points of their miniſtery to ſwerue from ſome obſervances which the lawes require. The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore will not follow, from the qualitie of the miniſtery, except hee can proue that our Miniſtery is in all our Aſſemblies, in all reſpects aimſwerable to our lawes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>Preeſthood</hi> which the law admitteth is not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sacerdotius</hi> but <hi>Presbyteratus,</hi> and the Prieſts are not called <hi>Sacerdotes</hi> or ſacrificers but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> (as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appeares by our orders in Latin.) Therefore the Law doth not intende any true and proper Prieſthood but onely boroweth the name to expreſſe an office of another kinde.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To bee Perſons, Vicars, Stipendaries, Chaplins, &amp;c. is not to haue a diuers kind of Prieſthood or deaconry, or Miniſtery (as hee fooliſhly conceiteth:) onely varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Tytles is giuen to the ſame kind of Miniſtery, in diuers perſons, in reſpect only of a diuers kinde of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce or dependance, for <hi>Parſons</hi> are ſuch as haue all tythes in kinde; <hi>Vicars</hi> ſuch as haue only the ſmaller Tyths, the other being impropriated by the Magiſtrate for other purpoſes; <hi>Stipendaries</hi> are ſuch as are maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the voluntary Contribution of their Churches or by ſome ſuch like meanes. <hi>Chaplins</hi> are ſuch as depend vpon great men; The Miniſtery of all which (If they duly execute the ſame) is one and the ſame, even that
<pb facs="tcp:177068:6"/>(and noe other for ſubſtance) which is proper to true Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is prooued by their 7. Arguments follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The. 1 Arg.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Paſtors and Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11. haue their offices, callings, adminiſtration and mainetenaunce ordained by Chriſt in his Teſtamente, Eph. 4.8.11.12. and Rom. 12.7.8. Act. 14.23. and 20.17.28. Heb. 5.4. Col. 4.17, 1. Theſ. 5, 12.13.14, 1. Pet. 5.1.2.3. Reu. 2. and 3. and 22.18, 1. Cor. 14.1. and 5.4. and 9.14. and 11.23. and 12.28. Gal. 6.6.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Prelates, Prieſts &amp; Deacons of the Church of England, haue not their offices, Callings, Miniſtration and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce ordained by Chriſt in his Testament.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo. <hi>They are not Paſtors and Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſſumption appeareth by their Conſtitution and practice, in as much as their offices of Prelacie, Prieſthood, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conry, their calling, and entraunce, according to their Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall, Their choyſe of their people, whoe ſtand themſelues vnder Antichriſt, and vnſeperated from the worlde, and are noe true viſible Churches of Chriſte. Their Ministration by their owne, and other Popiſh Canons, Artes Iniunctions, and booke of Common prayer, their maintenaunce by Tyths, Lordſhips &amp;c. were neuer ordained by Chriſt for his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but diriued from Antichriſt and his Apoſtaſye, as hath bene proued by vs in diuers treatiſes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. The Propoſition is not true, except hee vnderſtand by offices, Callings, and adminiſtration, the Subſtantial, or Eſſentiall parts therof. Otherwiſe thoſe very Paſtors
<pb facs="tcp:177068:6"/>and Teachers ther ſpoken of, may haue diuers acceſſary parts of their offices callings and adminiſtration not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned by Chriſt in the newe Teſtament. Nether is it true, Yf by maintenaunce hee meane any ſpeciall kind of maintenaunce. It is to be graunted in generall. That Miniſters, are to haue ſufficient maintenaunce, and the texts a ledged for that proues noe more, and therfore that which they proue, is nothing to the purpoſe; As little to the purpoſe are the other Texts, for it will not follow from any force in them, but that there may bee ſundry accidents cleauing as parts to the offices, calling, and maintenaunce of true Paſtors, and Teachers, which Chriſt neuer ordained.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Concerning the Aſſumption. 1. whether Prelates haue their office, calling &amp;c. ordained by Chriſt is beſids the preſent queſtion. Except M. Iohnſon can proue that they are ordinary Miniſters of our Church Aſſemblies; which I am ſure hee cannot. 2 Soe many of our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (whoe in the booke of ordination are called Prieſts and Deacons) as in all points concerning the ſubſtaunce of their Miniſtery, are qualified according to the intent of the lawes, haue their <hi>offices, callings, adminiſtration and maintenaunce</hi> for the ſubſtaunce therof, ordained by Chriſt: And yet I deny not, but ther may be ſome acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall defects, or Superfluityes in and a bout them all; yet ſuch as doe or cannot be proued to deſtroy the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſubſtance of any of them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. All that is brought to proue the Aſſumption is falce, and as much if not more controuerſal then the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe. For 1. hee can neuer proue, that either the practis of all our Miniſters, is in all things according
<pb facs="tcp:177068:7"/>to that Conſtitution, or their conſtitution according to their practis, or either of them anſwerable to the ſtrict termes of the law in all points. 2. Hee can neuer proue, that either in their conſtitution, or practis, or by the law they are in proper ſpeech, either Prieſts or Deacons; only hee preſumes them to be ſuch, becauſe through ſome libertie of ſpeech vſed in the lawes, they are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſuch. Though it ſhould bee graunted that our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtand vnder, ſome kinde of obſervances, and offices which in their owne nature, and firſt originall, are in ſome kinde Antichriſtian; Yet they are of ſuch a nature, that divers worthy Martyrs of Ieſus Chriſt, that haue with ſtood Antichriſt vnto blood, haue ſtood vnder as much as wee. And therfore ſuch a manner of ſtanding vnder Antichriſt, cannot be ſaid to overthrowe though it may ſomwhat ſtaine the Miniſtery of Chriſte. But howſoeuer, hee herein ſhamefully begs the queſtion, in the naked affirming, without any prooffe, <hi>That all in this kingdome are vnder Antichriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. Though (for avoyding further controuerſie) that ſhould be graunted him, that ſome parts of our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>by the Canons,</hi> &amp;c. was neuer ordayned by Chriſt. Yet at the leaſt the maine principall, and Eſſentiall parts therof performed according to the Canons and booke a foreſaid, are ordayned by Chriſt; yea by M. Iohnſon himſelf. Nether hath hee proued or euer can proue, That that part of our miniſtration, by our Canons, and booke a foreſaid, which Chriſt hath not ordayned (If any ſuch bee) is of that nature and qualitie, that it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryly deſtroyeth or maketh a nullity of the other parts of their Miniſtery, which vſe them.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:7"/> 5. Though Tythes and Lordſhippes and manners in perticulers, bee not ordayned by Chriſt for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of Miniſters, yet they are as much ordayned as any other particuler, or ſpeciall kind of maintenaunce, It is the will of Chriſt that the Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhould liue of the Goſpell. i. ſhould bee manietanied for their Miniſtery ſake by them to whome they preach the Goſpell. But in what particuler manner that maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce ſhould bee rayſed, hee hath noe wher defined and therfore left it to the diſcretion of Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates or Churches.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Wheras for the proofes of theis maine pointes, hee referreth vs to the generall Tytles of certaine Treatiſes formerly publiſhed, hee might as well ſend vs (as they ſay) to ſeeke a needle in a bottle of hay, and why doth hee not in all other points of this booke, as well as in the is, ſend vs to the ſaide Treatiſes? ſeeing hee ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing throughout this in effect, that hee hath not all ready ſaide in ſome one or other of his former bookes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Ioh. pag. 8.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Paſtors and Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 2. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>is the ordinary and perpetuall Miniſtery giuen by Christ to his Church, and ſuch as the Princes of the Earth nether may nor ever ſhall bee able to aboliſhe, ſeing Chriſt hath appoynted it to continue to the end of the worlde.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Prelacie Preeſthood, and Deaconrye of the Church of England is not the ordinarije and perpetuall Miniſtery giuen by Chriſt to his Church, but ſuch as the Princes of the Earth may and ought to aboliſh out of their Dominions. Rev. 17, 16 1. Tim. 2.2. Rom. 13, 4. with 1. Kin. 23.3. deu. 12.2. Pſa. 72.1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:8"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore the Preeſthood Prelacie and deaconrye of the Church of England is not the Ministery of Paſtors and Teachers ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Eph. 4.11.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Idenye the Aſſumption. Vnderſtanding by <hi>Prelacie Preeſthood and deaconrye,</hi> The ordinary Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies againſt which hee propounds to himſelf to Diſpute; And aunſwer. That it is the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and perpetuall Miniſtery, giuen by Chriſt to his Church, and ſuch as the Princes of the Earth are boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by Gods Lawes to maintaine and protect by their Authoritie; And if their bee any corruption in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the ſame, which they ought to aboliſh that yet they are accidentiall and perſonall; and not ſoe Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all as that they doe Diſtroy the Miniſtery.</p>
                     <p>The places of Scripture anexed to the Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the proofe therof, are all abuſed and profaned for not on of them doth any way ſoe much as colourablye proue either of the Clauſes in the Aſſumption, but only they proue in generall, That the Idolatry and Idolatrious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Antechriſt is to be aboliſhed: Soe that the man in his ſymplicitie, takes it as graunted; That our Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye is ſuch an Idolatrious Miniſtery; which is the maine matter in Controuerſy, and in effect the generall que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of his whole booke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn. pag: 9.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Office of Paſtors and Teachers ordayned by Chriſt in his Teſtament,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The. 3. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>are ſuch as did or could ſtand, with the offices of the Apoſtels, Prophetes and Euangeliſts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the offices of the Prelates, Prieſts or deacons of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:177068:8"/>of England, are not ſuch as did, or could ſtand, with or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the offices of Apostles, Prophets and Euangeliſts: which if any deny, let him ſhew the Countrary, by the Scriptures; Light hath no fellowſhip with darknes; nor Chriſt with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. And ſuppoſe the Apoſtles were a liue in their Perſons, and were in England, It were worth the knowing, whether they and the ordinances giuen by them, ſhould giue place to the Prelates, and their Canons, and whether they ſhould be ſuffred to preach, &amp;c. without ſubſcribing, and conforming. Their Canons vrge all vpon paine of Excommunication</hi> ipſo facto.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore they are not the Paſtors, and Teachers ordained by Chriſt in his nue Teſtament.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. What a ſhameleſſe man is this to affirme, <hi>That our Miniſtery nether did nor could ſtand with the offices of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles &amp;c.</hi> and for proofe therof bid vs, <hi>If we deny it ſhew the contrary by Scriptures.</hi> Doth not the burden of prouing by the very lawe of Common Reaſon ly vpon the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer? If I ſhould in like manner reproch his Miniſtery, &amp; ſay it is a Miniſtery that ſtandeth vpon Sorcery, witch croft and Coniuration and for proofe therof bid him, If hee deny it ſhew the countrary by Scripture, were I not worthy at leaſt to bee laughed out of the Scholes. This is a ſufficient juſtification of our Miniſtery; that ſuch Malitions aduerſaries therof, whoe woulde ſeeme ſoe expert in the Scriptures; are no better able by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to proue their vnchriſtian accuſation.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is true, <hi>that light hath noe followſhip with darknes, nor Chriſt with Antichriſt.</hi> Yet ther is no light in men in this
<pb facs="tcp:177068:9"/>life, but it is mingled with ſome darkneſſe; and the beſt Chriſtians that are, or euer haue bene ſince the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les times, may be infected with ſome points of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme. Many of the late Martyrs ſince the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Antichriſt, were worthy lights, and renoumed Chriſtians, and yet the light of many of them, was mingled with more darkneſſe, and their Chriſtianitie with more Antichriſtianiſme, then can be founde in our Miniſtery.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Our Biſhops haue as good reaſon, to make the like ſuppoſition againſt him, and as much worthy the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that were, if the Apoſtles, &amp;c. were a liue now in their owne Perſons where hee liueth, and ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Church Aſſemblies in Englande to be true Churches, and their Miniſtery in generall to be a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſtery, and their worſhip for ſubſtaunce to bee a true worſhip, whether M. Iohnſon and his Church would ſuffer them to be ſoe much as priuate members, of their Society, much more to preach, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Though our Biſhops ſhould herein be ſoe impious as to advance in ſuch a manner, their owne Authority, and ordinances aboue the Apoſtles. Yet what is that to proue that the Preeſthoode and Deaconry of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of our Church Aſſemblies, (who many of them in theis pointes are meere patients, and eſteeme of theis things as burdens) cannot ſtand with the offices of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp;c. doth M. Iohnſon think that none of our Miniſters in England would ſuffer the Apoſtles to preach in their Cures, without wearing a Surplice, If they might haue their owne wils, or ſhould this any whit derogate from their Miniſtery, that the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:9"/>Biſhops therin would not ſuffer them to haue their will.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. It is beſids the preſent queſtion, and a needleſſe thing to ſpend time in juſtifying the Canons herein: If the Biſhops therin haue gonne too far, it may ſeeme to bee the fault of the Parſons, rather then of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie it ſelfe, and therfore to make and vrge ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and Traditions as are a fore ſaide doth not proue, but that for all that, the Prelacie &amp; in of it ſelfe, might ſtand well enough with the offices of the Apoſtles &amp;c. for thoſe offices may of themſelues, (If their bee noe other impediment) ſtand well one with an other, which in the actions therof doe not (but by accident only) one overthrowe or oppugne the other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn. pag. 9.10.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The offices of true Paſtors,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 4. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>and Teachers are by the ordinaunce of Chriſt ſet in the Church, and imployd in the Miniſtery of the word, Sacraments &amp; Church Gouerment, ſoe as they may not, with their Eccleſiaſticall functions receaue Cyvill offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and callings, nor take vpon them princely Titles and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities. Eph. 4.11, 1. Pet. 5.1. Rom. 12.2.4. Luk. 12.14. and 22.25. 1. Cor. 12.5.8. 1. Tim. 4.13.15.16. 2. Tim. 2.4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the officies of Prelates, Prieſts, and Deacons of the Church of England, are not ſoe, but by their owne Conſtitution we ſet in the Church, and imployd in the Miniſtery ſoe as they may alſo receaue Cyvill offices and Callings, as to be Iuſtices of Peace, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore they are not true Paſtors and Teachers.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:10"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Ther are 4. Termes in this Syllogiſme, The groſſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſterye wherof may appeare by the Explanation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in others wordes.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>True Paſtors &amp; Teachers may not (viz. by Gods lawe) take vpon them Cyvill offices.</item>
                        <item>The Miniſters of England may (viz. by Mans lawe) take vpon them Cyvill offices.</item>
                        <item>Therfore they are not true Paſtors and Teachers.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>This is the effect of his Argument, &amp; who is ſo blind, but hee may ſee the fallacie therof. And it is as though we ſhould reaſon in the like manner againſt their owne Miniſtery, thus,</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>True Paſtors &amp; Teachers may not bee Drunckards, Anabaptiſts, Familiſts.</item>
                        <item>The Miniſters of the Seperation at Amſterdam may be Drunckards, Anabaptiſts, Familiſts.</item>
                        <item>Therfore they are not true Paſtors and Teachers.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>This Aſſumption is as true as the former, for the ſame kinde of Authoritie that permits our Miniſters to bee Cyvill Magiſtrats, doth permit them to bee Drunckards &amp;c. The goverment vnder which they liue, permitteth the one to more, then our ſtate doeth the other.</p>
                     <p>But I anſwer more particulerly.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That by the ſame lawe, that our Miniſters <hi>may</hi> take vpon them Cyvill Magiſtracie; Any true Paſtors, and Teachers, may take vpon them, the ſame Authority, and by the ſame lawe that true Paſtors and Teachers, may not take Cyvill Authoritye vpon them our Miniſters may not take the ſame vpon them.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:10"/>
                     <p n="2">2. All our Miniſters may not (noe by the lawes of our State) take vpon them Cyvill Authority; But ſuch only as are called ſpecially therto, by the fauours, &amp; grace of the Cyvill Magiſtrate, not as they are Prelats, Prieſts or Deacons, or by vertue of thoſe functions; but in reſpect of other qualifications. Nether are the forced by any law to adjoyne any ſuch Authoritie to their Miniſtery, but permitted only. But what if by the lawes of men, Miniſters might be Murtherers, Adulterers, Theeus, &amp;c. ſhould theis lawes chaunge the nature of their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? what? of their Miniſtery that denye vnto themſelues that lycence; would it not rather the more juſtify their Miniſtery; when in Conſcience of Gods law, they ſhall for beare that which fleſh, and blood and humaine laws would permit vnto them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Suppoſe not onely that it is vnlawfull for any true Paſtors, and Teachers, to bee Cyvill Magiſtrats, but that alſo by our lawes, all our Miniſters, were forced therunto, and that by vertue of their Miniſtery, will it thence follow, that for this cauſe, they are not true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers; May not true Paſtors and Teachers, in their weackneſſe, ignorance, and infirmities (the laws of the State requiring the ſame) admitt of ſome kind of office or Authoritie, for bidden them; but they muſt needs ther vpon ceaſe to bee true Paſtors, &amp; Teachers? doth the admitting of every vnlawfull thing chaunge the nature of the Miniſtery, and make it either noe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, or a Miniſtery of an other kinde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Chriſtian Paſtors, and Teachers,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The. 5. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>ſtandeth by
<pb facs="tcp:177068:11"/>the word, and ordinance of Chriſt, ſo as all Churches vnder Heaven, are bound to receaue, and ſubmit thervnto.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Prelacie, Preeſthood and Deaconry of the Ghurch of England ſtaundeth only by the Authoritie and Law of man, ſoe as other Churches els wher, nether are nor neede to bee ſubjecte thervnto; which euen themſelues of all ſorts haue acknowledged; for which ſee Whitgifts defence in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. The Anſwer to the Abſtraucte pag. 58. The Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Parlement; The defence of the Godly Miniſters the demonſtration.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is not the Miniſtery of Chriſtian Paſtors and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>I deny the Aſſumption. The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies of England, whether of Prelates, Prieſts or Deacons, or by what other names ſoeuer they be called, for the ſubſtance therof, ſtandeth by the word, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, and not onely by the Authority and law of man: And all other true Churches, are and ought to be ſubject, to the ſame kinde of Miniſtery, and to noe other, that ſhall in any Eſſentiall point of Miniſtery dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from ours.</p>
                     <p>If any Perticuler Parſons amongſt vs, haue bene ſoe vnaduiſed to graunt the Aſſumption, let them anſwer for themſelues; Hee hath noe more reaſon to binde vs to their opinions, then wee to binde him vnto what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer his predeceſſours Browne, Barrowe, and Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood haue held before him. Concerning ſome of the particulers, Doctor Whitgifts words are theis, <hi>The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:11"/>and nature of Gouerment muſt indeed by taken out of the word of God, and conſiſteth in theis parts. That the word be truely taught, the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, virtue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, vice repreſsed, and the Church kept in quietneſſe and order: The offices of the Church, wherby this Gouerment is wrought bee not namely, and particulerly expreſsed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but in ſome points left to the diſcretion, and libertie of the Church, to be diſpoſed according to the State of times, Places, and perſons.</hi> The Author of the Anſwer to the Abſtract in the place aledged ſaith, <hi>That it cannot be proued that any ſet and exacte particuler forme of diſcipline is recomended vnto vs in the word of God.</hi> Now are either of theis to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, <hi>That the Miniſtery of our Church Aſsemblies ſtaundeth only by the lawes and Authoritie of Man?</hi> Hath M. Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon any ſhame left in his face that thus ſhamefully abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the names of learned, and reuerent men, ſoe direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to their words and meaning. Is ther not cauſe to ſuſpect that the other Authors, are in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner abuſed, and that for the better hideing of his frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, hee forbeareth to quote any particuler places; Being therfore convinced of depravation, in the places parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly quoted, wee may preſume, that if the other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had bene more pertinent, hee would haue giuen vs ſome particuler directions alſo for the finding of them; And the rather, for that hee cannot be ignorant, that thoſe whom ſpecially hee fighteth againſt in theis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, doe rely vpon the judgement of the Authours following, more then of the former.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:12"/>
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The offices of Paſtors,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The <hi>6. Arg.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>and Teachers, which Chriſt hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are ſuch as they which haue them muſt bee members of a true viſible Church, and bound to one perticuler Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Miniſtery and Gouerment therof.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Offices of the Prelats, Prieſts, and Deacons of the Church of Englande, are ſuch as they which haue them, need not bee, neither in their State can bee members of a true viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, but of a fals, neither are bound to one perticuler Congregation for the Miniſtery and Gouerment therof, but the Prelates are our whoele Prouinces, and Dioceſſes &amp; other inferior Prieſts, may haue in that State pluralitie of benefices and Eccleſiall Cures &amp;c. which none can deny.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore they are not the Paſtors &amp; Teachers that Chriſt hath appointed.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Though ſome parts of the Propoſition bee diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; Yet becauſe other beſids the Seperation doe hould the whol for truth. I will leaue it <hi>in medio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption is falce; eſpecially if it bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode (as it ought to bee) of the offices of ſuch Prelats, Prieſts, and Deacons as are Miniſters of our Church Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies. For moſt of thoſe which haue ſuch offices are, and are bound to be members of true viſible Churches; And cannot in their Eſtate (they being in all points an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the lawes) be members of a falce Church; They are all (ſuch excepted as haue ſpeciall diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) bound to one particuler Congregation, and may not by law, haue more Cures then one; but admitting
<pb facs="tcp:177068:12"/>of a ſeconde, the firſt is voyd; Yea the Prelats the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues; though in regard of their Prelaticall office, they are Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of whole Prouinces, &amp; dioceſſes, yet it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them (not withſtanding) to be members (in their Eſtate) of a true viſible Church, and bee bound (as are the Prelats of Scotland) to one particuler congregation for the ſpeciall Miniſtery and Gouerment therof. And though the other Miniſters may haue in that eſtate pluralitie of benefices, and Cures, yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that therfore they are ſuch, as in their eſtate cannot be members of a true viſible Church; excepte they haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeede, yea &amp; though they ſhould be pluraliſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, yet (for ought hee hath proued to the contrary) they may bee membres of true viſible Churches, and may each bee bound to one particuler Congregation, for the Miniſtery and Gouerment therof.</p>
                     <p>But what man, except hee were halfe frantick, wold reaſon, thus, Our Miniſters may bee Pluraliſts therfore they neither <hi>are</hi> nor <hi>can be</hi> true Paſtors and Teachers; Is not this rather one of the honors then blemiſhes of our Miniſters; That they <hi>may be</hi> pluraliſts, and yet <hi>are not.</hi> If by our lawes their owne Aſſemblies were eſtabliſhed If by the ſame lawes their Paſtors and Teachers, might bee non reſidents or pluraliſts, or worſe, would they think hemſelus euer the worſe for this? would they not rather thinke themſelus the better that they are not ſoe bad, as by mans lawe they might bee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Offices Condition and Gouerment of Paſtors and Teachers,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 7. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>are ſuch as noe way impaire the Authority and Supremacy of the Syvill Magiſtrate.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:13"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the offices, Condition and Gouerment of Prelates, Prieſts &amp; Deacons, are ſuch as doe many waies impaire the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Supremacie and dignity of Kings, and all other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats both in Civill, and Eccleſiaſticall Cauſes. For the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates will haue their preſence, voice, and Authority, to be at Parlaments, for enacting of lawes and Statuts for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. They are Rulers of whol Prouinces, and dioceſses in the Eccleſiaſticall cauſes therof.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>In Civill State, and dignity, ſome of them are aboue all, and all of them, aboue ſome of the Nobles, Iuſtices, and other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats of the Lande. Themſelues their Courts and officers handle and determine ſundry Civill Cauſes, and affaires, appertaining to the Magiſtracie; They inflict Civill Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lts, and puniſhments; In their forbidden times they giue licence to Mary. The beneficed Prieſts ſweare Canonicall obeidience to the Prelats. All the Prieſts and Deacons are exempt from the Magiſtrats Iuriſdiction in diuers things appertaining vnto them, and anſwerable onely or cheifly to the Prelats and their officers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore they are not the onely Paſtors and Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Aſſumption is falce, nether doe the inſtances proue the ſame. 1. The Prelats claime their voices in Parlament not as diuine ordinaunces appartaining to their Prelateſhip, but as an honor annexed to the ſame by the Civill Magiſtrate.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Their Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſticall ouer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, &amp;c. is either ſuch as the Civill Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe may execute, and adminiſter in his owne perſon if
<pb facs="tcp:177068:13"/>hee pleaſe; or ſuch as is not for them, as they are Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, to execute. The firſt ſort they adminiſter only, by vertue of the Magiſtrats owne Commiſſion, and therin they cannot impair either his dignity, or Supremacie much leſſe in the other part of their Authoritie, which belongeth not to the Magiſtrats themſelues to execute eſpecially when they vſe it not nether, without their conſent, lycence, and approbation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That all are aboue ſome, and ſome aboue all of the Nobles, and Iuſtices, &amp;c. is a free and voluntary honour graunted vnto them by the Civill Magiſtrate, and held in tenure from him, and not claimed (as I thinke) as belonging to their Epiſcopall function, by diuine right.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Their Courts determine noe other Civill cauſes, then the Civill Magiſtrate, and his lawes do permit, or if they doe the falt is in the Parſons, and not in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latſhip; further they inflict Civill puniſhments, giue ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, exacte Oathes, &amp;c. by Authority from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat whoſe ſubſiſtutes therin they are. And therfore the Prelates neither in theis, nor in any of the former inſtances can bee ſaide to impaire the dignity, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or Supremacie of the Civill Magiſtrate, when herein they doe all things, in and by the protection of his Authoritie, much leſſe can other inferior Miniſters who haue noe dealing in the aforeſaid matters. Laſtly if all our Miniſters be exempt from the Magiſtrats Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, in ſome things appertaining vnto them (but wherin I knowe not) this very exemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe, is an act of the Magiſtrats Iuriſdiction &amp; depends, onely vpon his pleaſure! &amp; how can it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, any waies impair the ſame. &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:177068:14"/>hytherto hee hath dealt by Syllogiſmes ſuch as they are, now for a concluſion of this firſt Argument, hee ſhoots at rouers as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To this end diuers other reaſons might be aledged, for example If they ſay that Arch Biſhops haue the Paſtors, then they haue but two. If Lord Biſhops, then but 26. and what office then haue the Arch Biſhops amongſt them. If the other Prieſtes, then what office haue the Arch Biſhops: and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſeing God hath or dayned noe higher ordinary Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall office, as ſome of them-ſelus acknowledg. If they ſay the deacons haue the Paſtors office, the ſame abſurdity follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as in the former beſids that the works of the deacons office are oppoſed to the worke of the Miniſtery. Act. 6.2. with. Eph. 4.11. Rom. 12.8. If they ſhould ſay they haue the Teachers office, it would be known, which of their officiers haue it amongſt them, and to whom they are adioyned for the worke of Miniſtery, as Teachers are to Paſtors, and what office the reſt haue whom the accompt not to haue the Teachers office &amp; whether the Teacher ſpoken of Eph. 4.11. muſt firſt bee dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons; and then Prieſtes and permit obeydeince to the Prelates; and that alſo is to their ordinaires, and be ſylenced and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at thtir pleaſure.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Here hee thinkes hee hath knitt ſuch Gardian knotts as cannot be vntide, without a ſword or a bill; but the Simplicitie of the man here in is to bee laughed at, for 1. though ſome ſhould ſay, that either our Arch Biſhops: or Biſhops haue the Paſtors office, yet ther in they doe not exclude the other Miniſters, from that which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:14"/>and effect of that office, though they ſhould from the name; No nor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name neither, but ſhould ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in onely make degres of paſtours, viz. of Arch Biſhops. over Biſhops and their Dioceſſes of Biſhops over Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and their Churches, and of Miniſters ouer their owne Congregations; Leaving vnto them (not with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the Superioritie of the other Paſtors) that maine and Subſtantial office of the Paſtor which is enough to define and denominate a Paſtor. And therfore they may make ſuch Paſtors, as are over whole Prouinces but two, &amp; ſuch as are over whole dioceſſes but, 26. and yet hold alſo without any abſurditie, that their are alſo as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Paſtors beſyds, as ther are Miniſters of a particuler Congregation. And though it ſhould be graunted that herein they were deceaued in making Provinciall and dioceſme Paſtors; yet the ſorteing of vnproper Paſtors; with true or the ſubiecting of true Paſtors vnto other ſorts of Paſtors, doth not neceſſarily make the true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors fals, ſoe long as vnder them they performe, the name, and ſubſtantiall duties of true Paſtors; which all the Miniſters of our Church Aſſemblies doe, or by the lawes ought to doe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If any hould that the Miniſters of perticular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, onely are Paſtors, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they may without any abſurdity hould that they Arch Biſhops, and Biſhops, are generall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners vnder the King to ſee that the Paſtors doe their duties, and in that regard, may alſo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorically, and in another ſence bee called Paſtors, as Princes themſelves are ſoe called, in good and approued Authors; and what abſurdity can follow vpon this? Or what if they which hould the Miniſters of perticular
<pb facs="tcp:177068:15"/>Congregations to bee Paſtors, could not tell what to make of the office of Arch Biſhops and Biſhops, whats that to the purpoſe? are not our Miniſters, and Teachers therfore Paſtors, becauſe they which ſhall hould them to bee ſoe, cannot tell what to make of the Calling of Arch Biſhops and Biſhops?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Though this ſhould bee yelded vnto him that all Paſtors are equall, and that the Paſtors of perticular Congregations, are the higheſt ordinary Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call officers; yet ſhould this make nothing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of his conceit, That our Miniſters are not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore true Paſtors and Teachers, becauſe then Arch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops ſhould be excluded; for this doth not exclude them from being Commiſſioners, and Viſitors in cauſes eccleſiaſticall vnder the King over the Paſtors, and Churches, of ſuch and ſuch Prouinces and Dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which is to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their principall honour, &amp; due. 4. Concerning the Teachers office (not to contende needleſly, with him about the nature and quality therof but to ſuppoſe a Teacher in that ſence which hee mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) This may reaſonably bee held; That ſome of our Miniſters, (whether Prieſts or Deacons ſo called, or whether Parſons, Vicars, Curats or Stipendaries) are Paſtors and ſome Teachers, That ſo many of them as haue and vſe the gift, not onely of doctrine and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but of Exhortation, are Paſtors, That thoſe which wanting the power of Exhortation, and yet haue &amp; vſe the gift of inſtruction and doctrine are ſuch Teachers, as hee meaneth. And therfore herein alſo if it ſhould bee yealded vnto him, That it were fit that every Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſhould haue both theis offices; and that the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb facs="tcp:177068:15"/>ſhould be the Paſtors Aſſiſtant, yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but that in want of ſufficient men, for both theis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in every Congregation, ſome may inioy one, and ſome an other. For if the Churches of their owne way, and conſtitution, may bee without both Paſtors &amp; Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and that for a long time, till men may be choſen vnto that office? Why may not a Church much more in the like neceſſity retaine a Paſtor without a Teacher, or a Teacher without a Paſtor, Can hee proue by any colour out of Gods word, That one cannot bee called vnto, or execute the office of a Paſtor vntill hee haue a Teacher to aſſiſt him, or that hee cannot execute the office of a Doctor, except hee do it as an actuall aſſiſtant of ſome Paſtor? If not, then is this a moſt frivolous demaunde, when hee askes to whome our Teachers are adioynd for the worke of their Miniſtery: nether doe the places hee quoteth viz. Eph. 4.11. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 12.7. proue any ſuch matter. 5. As idle and impertinent is that demande which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <hi>whether the Teachers ſpoken of Eph. 4.11. muſt firſt bee Deacons, &amp; then Prieſts, &amp; promiſe obeidience to Prelats, &amp; be ſilenced and depoſed at their pleaſures.</hi> For what if noe ſuch matters bee required of Teachers by Paul, either in that or any other place, doth it thervpon follow, that their ſubmiſſion to ſuch things, makes them noe Teachers! may not Magiſtrats, &amp; others alſo require, ſome things of Teachers, not required by the Apoſtles, but they muſt needs thervpon, become no Teachers? But what repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauncie is their in theis matters, to the office of a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher? To be a Deacon in the intent of our lawes what is it, but (as himſelfe out of our booke of ordination hath in effect publiſhed it) <hi>To read the Seriptures,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp; to pray in the Church to Catechiſe the Io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſort, to baptize &amp; to preach
<pb facs="tcp:177068:16"/>if the Biſhop ſhal think him ſitt.</hi> what is it to bee a Prieſt, or Presbyter in our law? hath not himſelf alſo taught vs? viz.
<note place="margin">Pag. 32.</note> 
                        <hi>To haue authoritie to Preach the word, and to Miniſter the holy Sacramentes in the Congregation, wher hee ſhalbe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,</hi> what obeidience doe they (promiſe to Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the intent of the lawe? but onely in things that they ſhal judge honeſt, and lawfull, and not repugnaunt to the word of God; what is it to bee ſylenced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but to forbear to Miniſter publiquly (as themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues doe alſo forbeare) vpon the Magiſtrats pleaſure: for the Biſhops pleaſure ſoe far as they proceede according to the lawes, is the Magiſtrats pleaſure, otherwiſe it is but a perſonall fault. And wherein Imarvaile doe any of theſe acts, ſo oppugne the office of a Teacher, that they cannot ſtand together! wher doth Paul forbid any of theis acts vnto the Teacher? or if hee ſhould, doth euery Act forbidden to a Teacher, make him noe Teahcer?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn. pag. 14.</head>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Wheras ſome alledge that the people were to hear the Scribs and Phareſees ſitting in Moſes Chayre it is to bee noted, that they were Leuits and Prieſts and therfore had the true offices ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Moſes. This therfore is nothing for a fals Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſuch as theirs is proued to bee. further to bee a Pharefye was not to haue a new kinde of Miniſtery, but to bee of a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Sect amongſt the Iewes that pretended more ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the law, and might bee of any Tribe. Laſtly though the were corrupt, yet did the hould, that very true Miniſter muſt bee from heauen: and this haue the forward Preachers acknowledged, as T. C. pag. 83.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:16"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Here abſurdly, and Childiſhly hee goeth about to anſwer ſuch an objection, as noe body ever made againſt any thing contained in the former Argument. This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument onely is vſed in generall to ſhewe, that ſome corruptions in Miniſters and Churches are not of that nature, that men ſhould therfore ſeperate from all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Communion with them, And wher hee ſaith, that <hi>this is nothing for any fals Miniſtery neuer ordained of the Lord, ſuch as ours is proued to bee:</hi> Noe man ever brought it to proue any ſuch matter; But onely to proue that ſuch corruptions as are in our Miniſtery, ought noe more to hinder, communion with our Miniſters, then the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in the Miniſtery of the Scribes and Phareſees, did hinder the communion, with their Miniſtery, and that the corruptions in our Miniſtery doe noe more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue our Miniſters to bee fals Miniſters, then their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, did argue them to bee fals Miniſters: Nether hath hee brought any Argument to proue our Miniſters fals Miniſters, but either ſuch corruptions, as the Scribes and Phareſees were guilty of, in as high if not a higher degree, or in reſpect of their names, in that they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Prieſts and Deacons; So that if the Scribes &amp; Phare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees were true Miniſters, not with ſtanding their names, and other corruptions, our Miniſters cannot bee fals, in regard of the like names and corruptions: furthermore <hi>if to be expounders of the Law,</hi> bee ſufficient to argue their Miniſtery to bee a true Miniſtery, nothwithſtanding their names of Scribes and Phareſees, with other vile &amp; groſſe corruptions; why may not the Preaching of the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:17"/>word, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to argue, our Miniſters to bee true Paſtors, and Teachers, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that in the mouth of the law, they are ſometimes called Prieſts and Deacons. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in the mouths of men; euen of the Biſhops themſelues they are not ſo called; except ſometimes by Metaphoricall alluſions to the Leviticall Preeſthood; But they are vſually ſo called onely by profane Atheiſts, or ignorant people, with whom in this point, the Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration goeth hand in hand.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To bee a Phareſie was not onely (as hee minceth the matter) <hi>to be of a ſpeciall Sect amongſt the Iewes, that pretended more ſtrict obſeruances of the law then others.</hi> But alſo (which as it is to be feared with a fraudulent minde hee concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth) to joine mainy humaine Traditions, and will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to the worſhip and ſeruice of God (wherby they are ſaide by Chriſt himſelfe, in vaine to worſhip God, and to make the commaundements of God of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;) making more accompt of; and vrging with more ſeverity the ſaid Traditions, then Gods owne laws; And in like manner, wee affirme, That to bee a Prieſt and Deacon, in the intent of our law (whatſoeuer the words may ring to the contrary in ſome mens eares) is (at the worſt) to bee ſuch a kinde of paſtor and Teacher, as is content, over and beſids thoſe duties of the Miniſtery which Chriſt requires of them to yeald conformity al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to humaine Traditions, of noe worſe nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in themſelues, then thoſe which the Phareſies vſed in or about Gods ſeruice, wherin to ſuppoſe that they ſin, yet cannot this their ſin be ſo repugnant to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Chriſt as that of the Scribes and Phareſies,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:17"/>which they are forced to acknowledge to be a true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, In that they were the vrgers of Traditions, wheras our Miniſters (for the moſt part) onely yeald vnto them, either in obeidience and loue; or feare of the Magiſtrat that commaundes them. Laſtly wheras hee argues them true Miniſters by this, <hi>that though they were very corrupt, yet the did ſtill hould that euery Miniſtery muſt bee from Heaven, and not of men.</hi> It deſerues rather to bee lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed at, then anſwered. For may not yea doe the falſeſt Miniſtery that are or ever haue bene, hould ſo much, at leaſt in ſuch a ſence and meaning as the Phareſies might hould it. And can hee name any amongſt vs, that houlds not as much?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE SECOND REASON. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Ihon.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>NOne may heare or haue any Spiritually communion with the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>None may heare haue any Spirituall communion with the ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:18"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>I graunt the Propoſition; taking the words in the plaine and common ſence viz. vnderſtanding by <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtacie.</hi> The adminiſtration and diſpenſation of the things of Antichriſt; otherwiſe to communicate ſpiritually with any Miniſters what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer onely in the holy things of Chriſt, is not to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtacy, no though the Miniſters be Miniſters therof. Nether do the 5. Reaſons following whereby hee needleſly proues his prepoſition, proue it vnlawfull to heare or haue any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall communion with the Miniſters of Antichriſt, then, when they Miniſter the things of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>For the profe of the Aſſumption hee makes a terrible muſter if no leſſe then 7. Arguments. But let vs pull vp our Spirets, and ſee what is in them, one by one.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts ordained by the Prelats thervnto is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 1. Arg.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande, is ſuch a Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Hee brought this very Argument to proue the firſt Reaſon and now hee brings it againe for a profe of his ſecond Reaſon: And is not this a learned kind of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning? when hee will make a ſhew of multitudes of
<pb facs="tcp:177068:18"/>Reaſons againſt vs, and yet all of them come to one iſſue and lie vpon one ground, and depend vpon one profe; ſo that the overthrowe of one, is the overthrowe of all: But his childiſh vanitie herein wee ſhall better perceaue in that which followeth.</p>
                     <p>Both the Propoſition and Aſſumption are fals; For 1. It is not neceſſary, that the Miniſtery of Prieſts, and Deacons, though ordained by Antichriſt himſelfe, ſhould be the Miniſtery of his Apoſtacy; But not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his ordination, their Miniſtery may be the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Ieſus Chriſt; As was the Miniſtery of Luther, Huſſe, Wickliffe and others.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Miniſtery of ſuch manner of Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, as the Prelats ordaine, (or by the lawes ought to ordaine) is the true Miniſtery of Ieſus Chriſt, and for the ſubſtance therof, directly contrary to the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies, is not (as I haue ſhewed before) the Miniſtery of Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons properly ſo taken, but of Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                     <p>The Propoſition hee proueth as followeth by two Arguments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts which accompts it ſelfe to bee Chriſts, and yet was not ſet by Chriſt in his Church, for the worke of his Miniſtery, is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts, ordained by the Prelats therevnto.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:19"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Argument is it which hee bringeth for the firſt Reaſon of all; and here hee brings it to proue that which before was brought to proue it. For hee proues, <hi>That our Miniſtery is not ſet by Chriſt in his Church, by this becauſe it is the Miniſtery of Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> and ſo by conſequent of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie. Here hee proues, <hi>That the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Prieſts and Deacons is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie, Becauſe it is a Miniſtery, that was not ſet by Chriſt in his Church;</hi> This doth hee moſt groſly runne round in a circle, as if I ſhould proue that his Miniſtery is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe hee is a Schiſmatick, and that hee is a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, becauſe his Miniſtery is vnlawful. The 2. Reaſon wherby he proues his Propoſition followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. If the Prelates of the Church of England haue ſuch offices, and Gouerment as be ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie, then the Miniſtery ordained by them thervnto muſt needs bee the Miniſtery of that Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Prelats of the Church of England haue ſuch offices and gouerment, as bee ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore the Miniſtery ordained by them is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The conſequent is manifeſt, becauſe the fruit muſt needs bee as the tree is. Mat. 7.16. and who can bring a clean thing out of filthineſse. Iob 14.4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is proued.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. Whoſoever (beſids Chriſt) haue ſuch offices and Gouerment, wherby the claime to bee ſpirituall Lords, the haue the offices,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:19"/>and Gouerment which are ſpeciall parts of Antichriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy, and are indeed very Antichriſts themſelues.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But ſuch are the Prelats of the Church of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore the haue ſuch offices and Gouerments, as are ſpeciall purts of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Propoſition is proued by thoſe places of Scripture which teach that there is but one ſpirituall Lord, the Lord Ieſus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is proued by the lawes, and Statutes of the land, wherin they are called Lords Spirituall, and in their Canons they take vpon them to preſcribe their owne ordinaunces to the Ghurch for the worſhip of God, and binde the ſpiret and couſcience to the acknowledgement, and approbation therof, and to giue the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. The offices and Gouerment of ſuch Biſhops, as are ouer Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan, and Prouinciall Churches, and exerciſe Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction ouer all the Miniſters and people therin, are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall parts of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But ſuch are the Prelates of the Church of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They haue ſuch offices and gouerment as bee ſpecially parts of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. I deny the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent of the Propoſition of the 1. Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme. The officers &amp; gouernors of Antichriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy, may &amp; haue ordained ſome things that are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Nether doth the ſaying of Chriſt or Iob proue the conſequent; for though it ſhould be graunted vnto him, that the gouernors of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy haue ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Miniſtery; yet doth it not follow that it is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a propre &amp; meere fruit of Antichriſt, but may be an
<pb facs="tcp:177068:20"/>dentall effect, as are many other things which hee ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth agreable to Chriſts owne ordinaunces, ſo that hee muſt proue that our Miniſtery ordained by the Pope or Biſhops, doth as properly flowe from the nature of their office and gouerment, as figs from a fig tree, or grapes from a vine, or filthy water from a foule fountaine; The contrary wherof is in this caſe moſt euident. For leaue the bare names and tytles, and conſider our Miniſtery in all the eſſentiall parts, and offices therof, and it is a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, either for a <hi>Presbythery,</hi> or for any perticuler Church, ſuch in conſtitution as their owne, to ordaine the like Miniſtery in all points and reſpects, with all the defects and faults therof.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Concerning the firſt profe of the Aſſumption, The Propoſition may bee denied; It being one thing <hi>to bee,</hi> and another to <hi>make claine to bee,</hi> for euery one is not that which hee claimeth to bee, The Inſtances alledged to proue the Aſſumption, either are fals or proue it not. The lawes may giue their titles, to men which they doe not claime. Neither doe either their Canons or practis ſhew that they preſcribe their owne ordinances <hi>for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> or propound to <hi>binde mens conſciences to the acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of any ſuch matter.</hi> The profeſſe the contrary, and vrge their owne ordinaunces onely vnder the name of things indifferent, Though therfore in error of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they may, and happily doe commande ſuch ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of their owne, as are diuine worſhip, and in ſuch a manner as it bindeth conſcience (which M. <hi>Iohnſons</hi> owne Church in many caſes may doe, except they think themſelues priviledged from error) yet they proteſting againſt any ſuch power and authority, they cannot be
<pb facs="tcp:177068:20"/>ſaide therin to arrogate the office of Spirituall Lords, in that ſence at leaſt, in which Chriſt is ſaid to bee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirituall Lord. And though in their ordination of Miniſters, they vſe as a ceremoniall ſpeech to ſay, <hi>Receaue the holy Ghoſt;</hi> and therin peraduenture offer ſome force vnto the Scripture vnto which the allude; yet they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime al actuall power and authority of giuing the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or gifts of the holy Ghoſt vnto men.</p>
                     <p>It ſhall bee needleſſe in this controverſie, to ſpend time in the defence of the calling of Biſhops any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the neceſſity of the argument requires, Onely for the further clearing of the truth in the differences of them of the Seperation not only from the Biſhops, but from the other ſort of Miniſters alſo, which doe not approue of their callings, I offer theis pointes vnto them to conſider of adviſedly.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Whether the Supreame Magiſtrate haue not power to ouer ſee, and Gouerne all the ſeverall Churches with in his dominions, yea whether hee bee not bound ſo to doe?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whether for his further helpe and aſſiſtance herein hee may not make choiſe of graue learned and reuerent men to aſſiſt him in the ſame gouerment.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whether by vertue of his power theis perſons thus called to aſſiſt the Supreame Magiſtrate, may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully try the gifts of all the ſeverall Miniſters with in his dominions, and giue publique approbation of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, &amp; inhibit thoſe which they finde vnworthy, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the execution of their Miniſtery, &amp; whether they may not viſit the ſeverall Miniſters and Churches, conuent them before them, examine them, how they haue behaued
<pb facs="tcp:177068:21"/>themſelues in their places, and puniſh the blame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Whether for the more eaſy and orderly Gouerment of the ſaid Churches, ſo far forth as appertaineth to him, hee may not devide his kingdom (as ours is) into Provinces aſſigning over each of them vnder himſelf ſome ſpeciall Magiſtrat for learning and experience to overſee, and gouerne all the perticuler Churches there, and whether hee may not ſubdevide thoſe Provinces into Dioceſſes, aſſigning alſo to them, other more infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior officers, vnder him, and his provinciall officers, to over ſee the ſeverall Churches with in ſuch, and ſuch a precincte?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Whether it doe deſtroy the nature of a Miniſteriall or a perticular true viſible Church, that many of them ſhould appertaine vnto one Provinciall or Dioceſame gouerment, though in that reſpect they ſhould bee held and reputed, but for one Provinciall, or Dioceſame Church?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Whether Antichriſt hauing vſurped the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and taken into his hands this authority and corrupted the ſame, hath made it now vnlawfull for the Magiſtrate to execute the ſame in manner and forme a fore ſaide; or whether the Iuriſdiction a fore ſaide doe not directly and properly belonge to the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and not to Antichriſt. But by vſurpation; And whether his vſurpation of this office can make it a part of his Apoſtaſie in thoſe places where it is reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Supreame Magiſtrate.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Whether the Supreame Magiſtrate recerving this his right from Antichriſt, and together with it happily
<pb facs="tcp:177068:21"/>taking alſo to himſelfe ſome thing alſo that belonges to the Kingdom of Antichriſt: &amp; executing the ſame either in his owne perſon or by others, together with his owne lawfull right, whether (I ſay) this doe deſtroy his owne lawfull right? and whether the ſubiect is ever the leſſe bounde to ſubject themſelues vnto the ſame right, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his owne perſon, or his ſubſtitute.</p>
                     <p>Hither to hee hath indevoured to proue the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt Argument, wherby hee would confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, the Aſſumption of his 2. reaſon, and now hee ſets v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the profe of the Aſſumption. Namely, <hi>That the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande, is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Deacons, and Prieſts ordained by the Prelats ther vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> This hee ſaith is proued by the Canons conſtitutions &amp; obſeruation of our Church; And this hee confirmeth firſt by a longe, tedious and idle reherſall of the forme of ordination of our Miniſters, beſtowing coſt to print, in a manner our whole booke of ordination.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By certaine of the late Canons preſſing ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conformity, and an acknowledgement of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of the calling of Biſhops, and of their ordination.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. By certaine ſharpe ſpeeches of ſome Martyrs and of ſome others of our owne Nation againſt the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhohs, &amp; other of the cleargy of their times. In the relation of which pointes hee ſpends ſome 5 lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves; wherin ſtill hee runs in a circle begging one of his arguments to proue an other, So that one of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are as good as all, and all no better then one; This may ſuffice for anſwere. 1. That if all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars mentioned in the booke of ordination ſhould bee ſtrictly, and preciſely practized (as alwayes they are
<pb facs="tcp:177068:22"/>not) yet ther is not one clauſe in the whole forme of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by him cited, that doth neceſſarily argue them, which are ſo ordained, to bee true and proper Prieſts, and Deacons; But if ther were and if alſo the Miniſters ordained, were anointed with oile, if their crownes were ſhawen, and they had power giuen to offer the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable Idole of the Maſſe, yet this is not ſufficient to argue, that their Miniſtery is the Miniſtery of Prieſts, &amp;c. except in their Miniſtery they ſhould execute the ſame. If their owne Church ſhould ordaine one to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of a Paſtor, and ſhould in their ordination require him only to preach the worde ſincerely, and to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacraments according to Chriſts inſtitution, and yet in his practis and execution, hee ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but ſing Maſſe and Mattens, and they ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this Miniſtery, and no other, at his hands; would any that is in his wits, ſay that this mans Miniſtery, is the Miniſtery of a Paſtor: becauſe hee was in formality of words &amp; ceremonies ordained to that office, how much leſſe can any ſay that our Miniſtery is the Miniſtery of Prieſts, when they doe not only execute any ſuch office, but the clean contrary; and when in their ordination not ſo much as any parte of a Prieſts office (properly ſo taken) is aſſigned vnto them, but only the name; and not ſo much as their name in their orders written in Latin, which are to interpret the meaning of the Engliſh worde.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Though the Miniſters ſhould doe all things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the canons, and ſhould bee every way anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto them, And though the Teſtimonies of our Martyrs and others were yealded to bee true, yet muſt
<pb facs="tcp:177068:22"/>hee ſtreiue hard, that can from either or both, argue that our Miniſters, are indeede Prieſts, except in a Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall, and borrowed ſpeech.</p>
                     <p>The other Arguments wherby hee proueth the maine Aſſumption of the 2. Reaſon viz. <hi>That the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of England, is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy,</hi> followe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of the Prelacie profeſsing it ſelfe to bee Chriſts,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 2. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>and yet ſtanding in ſuch an eſtate as it doth not obey Ieſus Chriſt in his ordinance of Miniſtery, worſhip and gouerment of the Church, as their Prophet, Prieſt and King, is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the preſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>To the Propoſition I anſwer, That not onely the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the Prelates,</hi> but of a Presbytery, or any Church whatſoever that ſtands in ſuch an eſtate, is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtacie; And not onely the Miniſtery of the Prelats, but any other Miniſtery els vpon earth, may ſtand in ſuch an eſtate, as that it may in diuers, and ſundry Perticulers of (ignorance or infirmity) diſobey Chriſt in his owne ordinances of Miniſtery, worſhip, and gouerment of the Church, and in that reſpect, and ſo far forth bee the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy, &amp; yet bee alſo the Miniſtery of Ieſus Chriſt. Hee proues
<pb facs="tcp:177068:23"/>the Propoſition by 19. places of Scripture; to as much purpoſe, as if by as many Teſtimonies, hee ſhould proue that it is day lighte at high noone; Except hee meane, That that is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie, doth not in euery perticuler obey Chriſt in his owne ordinances of Miniſtery. But which his 19. proofes haue no more force to proue it, then to proue that their is a man in the moone, as any may ſee that hath nothing els to doe, but to examine them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. I deny the Aſſumption; The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies, though it bee ordained by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, and bee ſubject vnto them, yet it is not their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, but the Miniſtery of Ieſus Chriſt; They preaching his worde, &amp; adminiſtring his Sacraments; And it doth (if it bee anſwerable to the law:) obey Chriſt in all the maine eſſentiall parts of his owne ordinaunce of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, &amp;c. And in all other points (for ought hee can proue to the contrary) as far as the Lord hath revailed the truth vnto them which exerciſe the ſame.</p>
                     <p>But (ſaith hee) the <hi>Aſsumption is evident by that which hath bene ſaid in the 1. Reaſon and their Conſtitution it ſelfe ſhewes it, in that they are ſo farre from obeing Chriſt in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Miniſtery &amp;c. as that they execute the Miniſtery and gouerment of an other Arch Biſschop, L. Biſhop then Chriſt of an Arch-Deacon, Parſon, Vicar, &amp;c. as alſo in their reading; prayers out of a booke, and obſerving other humaine inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in their Church Gouerment according to Canons, Courts, &amp;c. which were neuer appointed by Chriſt.</hi> To omit that here againe, hee begs his firſt reaſon to proue his ſeconde, If the Aſſumntion haue noe better evidence, the evidence is fals, as I haue made it evident, in the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:23"/>Anſwer to the firſt reaſon? Nether hath hee there or els where (in any of thoſe other of their wrightings which hee ſends vs vnto <hi>pag. 40.</hi>) proued that our Miniſters do not obey Chriſt, in his ordinance of Miniſtery, worſhip, and Gouerment, yea though it ſhould be graunted that they execute the Miniſtery, and Gouerment of other Arch Biſhops, and L. Biſhops beſids Chriſt. And though they ſhould bee Arch Deacons, Parſons, Vicars, reading ſtinted prayers, &amp;c. For all this may bee donne yea and they may ſinne ſome way in doing all this, and yet they may obey Chriſt in all the maine eſſentiall and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall pointes of his Miniſtery worſhip and Gouerment.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Chriſtians which is oppoſed againſt and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue the holy things, Miniſtery &amp; ordinances of Chriſt,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 3. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>is the Miniſtery of Autichriſts Apoſtaſie, 2. Theſ. 2.3.4. with 1. Ioh. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of their Church Aſsemblies.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is euident, 1. Aman may peaceably receaue or adminiſter, their holy things in their manner, by vertue of their Deacoury or Prieſthoode, receaued from their Prelats.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But if any doe adminiſter or receaue the holy things of God by the offices of Paſtors, and Teachers entred into and executed according to the Teſtament of Chriſt, they are reviled and perſecuted.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. Their Prelacie, Prieſthoode, and Deaconry is the very meanes of thruſting away and keeping out of the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:24"/>Church the Miniſtery and order which Chriſt hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which ſome of themſelues hereto fore haue acknowledged, and written.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies being anſwerable to the lawes, is not a Miniſtery exalted in any thing, aboue the Miniſtery of Chriſt, but the very ſame in nature and qualitie, though in ſome accidents it may differ. In which difference, if ther bee any ſinne, it is of ignorance, or infirmitie in the Miniſters; which may in as high or a higher degree befall vnto the beſt Miniſters that ever were ſince the Apoſtles times.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The holy things which they adminiſter are the holy things of Ieſus Chriſt, and not of their owne, &amp; by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Prieſthoode and Deaconry which they haue receaued they may not adminiſter any other holy things but what Chriſt Ieſus requireth. The other things which they adminiſter are iudged by them which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter them; onely things indifferent and matters of order, wherein if they which vſe them be deceaved, it is but ſuch an error as worthy Martyrs of Ieſus Chriſt haue bene ſubject vnto, and not ſufficient to make their Miniſtery an Antichriſtian Miniſtery.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Prelats doe not perſecute any true Paſtors and Teachers, ſo much for Miniſtering any of the holy things of Chriſt, as for refuſing to conforme to ſome ſpeciall ordinances of their owne, which they doe not hould to bee holy things, but matters of order, &amp; which by reaſons they haue indevoured to proue to bee ſo: wherein the practis of Prelats is noe more extreame,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:24"/>then their owne, who cenſure as farr as they can, in all extremity, all them whoe doe not in al points, conforme and agree to their owne orders, ceremonies and Church policie.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. It can never bee proued, that the admittance of this Miniſtery, is a hindrance of a better, but rather it is a meanes to keepe out a wors, and away in time to bring in a better, if a better bee to be brought in, for by yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſome things that may be bettered &amp; is ſo wiſhed and indeavored, a dore is opened to Miniſter many holy things, which otherwiſe ſhould bee ſhut. And if it bee as lawfull, for vs to conjecture, as for him, Their general Schiſme and rent from this Miniſtery, hath bene one maine and principall meanes to vphoulde it as it is.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery which is ſuch as in the nature and condition therof it pertaineth not to any body or eſtate either civill or eccleſiaſticall but only to the body or kingdome of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 4. Arg.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of their Church Aſsemblies.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is clear, in as much as their Prelacie, Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Deaconry; is ſuch that the Civill State may bee perfect without, them and the Church of Chriſt may bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat without them, onely the body, and Kingdome of the Romiſh Antichriſt, cannot bee full and furniſhed in all the offices therof without them.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:25"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>For Anſwere to the Aſſumption,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Concerning the Prelacie (though it bee not any Miniſtery of any of our Church Aſſemblies, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Idly vrged, in this and all the other Arguments) this may bee ſaide; 1. That the principall, and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable parts therof is onely vſurped by Antichriſt, and doth not appertaine to him, but to the Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Supreame Magiſtrats, and States.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That the State of a Chriſtian common wealth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee perfect, without ſome generall viſitors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers of Churches. 3. That though a perticuler Church or congregation may bee compleat without them, yet for the neceſſary vnion, and agreement of the ſeverall Churches in Chriſtian Provinces, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, it is fit and agreable to reaſon, and noe wayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Gods word, that vnder the Supreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ther ſhould bee, other Governors to protect, and incorrage thoſe Miniſters, and Churches which doe their dutie, and to puniſh thoſe which ſhall offende. Wherin if either through warrant of humaine lawes, or ſome perſonall corruption, they ſhall in ſome things paſſe their bounds, they doe no more then any other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers either Civill or Eccleſiaſticall, through frailtie, &amp; infirmitie may doe. 4. That the kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt cannot be furniſhed, in all the offices therof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Authority of Civill Magiſtrats, and therfore this ſeemes to make as much againſt the calling of civill Magiſtrats as Biſhops.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Concerning the Miniſtery of our Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:25"/>ſuch as it is, or by lawe ought to be in our Church Aſſemblies, the Church of Chriſt cannot bee compleat without it; yea it is noe Church without it. Nether can the kingdome of Antichriſt ſtand before it, Nether will hee ever proue the contrary.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery which is ſuch as the body of Antichriſt the man of ſinne,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 5. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>cannot without it be compleat in all the members and canonicall functions therof is the Miniſtery of Autichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is proued by the Canons, Pontificall, and eſtate of the Romiſh Antichriſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Argument is but the taile of the former, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needs noe further Anſwer, it being cut of in the anſwer to the former. The Canons Pontificall, &amp; State. of the Romiſh Antichriſt doe manifeſt the countrary, which haue and doe curſe and perſecute with ſworde and fier, ſuch a Miniſtery as is the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies: if it bee in all points to the intent of the law.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Miniſtery of Deacons, Prieſts, and Prelates which accounts it ſelfe to be Chriſts, and yet indeed is ſuch, as the Kings and Rulers of the Earth may and ought to ſuppreſse, and roote out of their dominions, is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:26"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is their Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therefore it is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is proued in the former reaſon and in other Treatiſes, and by ſome of themſelues in their Suites to Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and if the Prelats and their conforming cleargy, deny it they are by their owne Canons exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated</hi> ipſo facto.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This ſixt Argument is borrowed from the firſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wher it is brought to proue that our Miniſtery is not the Miniſtery of Paſtors and Teachers, as here it is brought againe to proue, that it is the Miniſtery of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Apoſtaſy; Thus then hee reaſoneth, the King may and ought to ſuppreſſe this Miniſtery, Therfore it is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſy. But how doth hee proue, That the King ought to ſuppreſſe this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? Hee refers vs for the proofe therof eſpecially to the former Reaſon, how doth hee proue it ther? Thus. It is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie. Therfore the king ought to ſuppreſſe it. Is not this learned ſtuffe?</p>
                     <p>Concerning his other Treatiſes, which hee ſo often ſends vs vnto, as if they were in every ſtreete and market place of the lande, wee haue not ſo much idle time to ſeeke after them: and wee preſume wee ſhall find noe better ſtuffe in them then in this; If any amongſt vs haue put vp any ſuch ſuit to the Parlament, for the Abol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of our Miniſtery in generall, let them anſwer for themſelues; But the Prelats may well laugh at his ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and ſeelineſſe of wit, that thinks to fright them with ſuch a bug-beare as this, in making them beleeue that they are by their owne Canons excommunicated
<pb facs="tcp:177068:26"/>
                        <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> if they deny that the King may, and ought to aboliſh our Miniſtery.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>If it bee ſuch as ſhall bee aboliſhed by the Lord throughout the power, and light of his Goſpell,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">The 7. Arg.</note> 
                           <hi>then is it the Miniſtery of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The firſt is true.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore the latter is true alſo.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The ſame anſwer will ſerue to this Argument, that was giuen to the former; For the Aſſumption is fals, The light of the Goſpell ſhall more, and more, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme eſtabliſh, and perfect it, and remoue all the defects and blemiſhes in it, his profe is as ridiculous, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticall, as is the former; for hee proues it by the ſame queſtion, that here it is brought to proue, for ſo in effect proceeds his diſputation.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>That which ſhall bee aboliſhed is Antichriſtian.</item>
                        <item>Our Miniſtery ſhall bee aboliſhed.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is Antichriſtian.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>But how doth hee for our learning proue that our Miniſtery ſhall bee aboliſhed, very learnedly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly thus.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>That which is Antichriſtian ſhall be aboliſhed.</item>
                        <item>Our Miniſtery is Antichriſtian.</item>
                        <item>Therfore it ſhall be aboliſhed.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>For this is the effect of that idle diſcourſe of 2. or 3. leaues, viz. pag. 46.-51. tending to proue, That Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and all his offices ſhall be aboliſhed.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:27"/>
                  <head>THE THIRD REASON. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>WHat ſoever Miniſtery is ſuch none can heare or haue any ſpirituall communion with it, but in ſo doing hee ſhall worſhip the Image of the beaſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue his Marke, in his forehead or hand. That Miniſtery may none heare, or haue any ſpirituall communion with all.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the preſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of England, is ſuch as none can heare or haue any ſpirituall Communion therwith but in ſo doing hee ſhall worſhip the Beaſts ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and receaue his marke in his forehead or hand.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>None may heare or haue any Spirituall communion therwith.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Reaſon for the effect and ſubſtance therof diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not from the ſeconde, for what is it (by his owne interpretation) <hi>to worſhip the beaſts image, but to ſubiect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Miniſtery, and worſhip of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie,</hi> and how is it poſſible for him to proue this but by runing to the former Reaſons, for their help therin.</p>
                     <p>For the profe of the Aſſumption hee ſets vs downe a tedious and impertinent diſcours of ſome ſix leaues of paper, teaching what is meant by the beaſt &amp; his Image,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:27"/>and by receaving the marke in the forehead or hand, The ſome and effect wherof is this,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That by Beaſt wee are to vnderſtand the Romaine Dominion and Antichriſts hierarchie, withall the offices, lawes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pag. 51.—63.</note> 
                        <hi>and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity appertaining thervnto, That by worſhipping the Beaſts I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage may bee vnderſtoode the yealding of ſpirituall ſubiection to that Antichriſtian kingdome in the lawes offices and Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction therof, That by receaving the marke in the forehead or hand, is publiquely to profeſse and obſerue them not being a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the beaſts wayes. And this doe all they who ſubmitte to the goverm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>et of Prelats, Prieſts, Parſons, Vicars, booke worſhip, &amp;c.</hi> Not to contende about this interpretation, but to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it true, ther is nothing in ſubſtance here brought to confirme the 3. Reaſon, but that which is in the 2. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, viz. that therfore wee worſhip the beaſt, in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating with our Miniſtery, Becauſe it is the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie. And therfore it needs noe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Anſwer, then what hath bene giuen already. Only thus much further, That for men ſo far forth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Gouerment of ſuch Prelats, &amp;c. as our lawes doe require, is not <hi>to yealde ſpirituall ſubjection to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Antichriſte,</hi> nor without ſhame to profeſſe the Beaſts wayes. For they may not withſtanding that bee ſubject to Chriſt and his lawes, and to fight againſt the beaſt. Yea though it ſhould be graunted, that ther, in ſundry perticulers they yeald to ſome things, in their vſe Antichriſtian and vnlawfull; which the beſt reformed Churches and Miniſters, ſometimes of ignorance or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity may doe; and yet remaine the Churches and Miniſtery of Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:28"/>
                  <head>THE FOVRTH REASON. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>NOne may heare or joine in any Spirituall Communion with that Miniſtery which deriveth not their power and function of Miniſtery from Chriſt, which is the head for the edification of his Church, which is his body.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of England.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore none may heare or joyne in Spirituall Communion therwith.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This reaſon is the ſame with the firſt; for it is all one, <hi>To be derived from Chriſt,</hi> &amp;, <hi>To be ſet by Chriſt in his Church,</hi> The other words which here hee addeth, Doth noe more vary the force of the Argument, then a new gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment put vpon the ſame witneſſe would make him a nue and different witneſſe from himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>In the profe of the Aſſumption hee daubes 6. pages, bringing therin, nothing but his ould brokery, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherof is as followeth.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Pag. 64.—70.</note> 
                           <hi>That our Miniſters haue not theſe offices which Chriſt hath giuen to his Church for the worke of his Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. That it is the Miniſtery of Deacons and Prieſts made by the Prelats.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:28"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3. That they were left in England by the Pope, and are ſtill in the Kingdome of Antichriſt wher they firſt roſe, and theefore is deviliſh, and by conſequent the more gifts and truth the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters bring with them, the more the vphould the Miniſtery of iniquitie, and intiſse vnto their ſtolne waters and hid bread.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4. That our Church aſsemblies are not true viſible Churches of Chriſt vnſeperated from the worlde not joyned together in Communion of the Goſpell by voluntary Profeſsion of the faith and ſubmiſsion to the Gouerment of Chriſt, but ſtanding in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnto Antichriſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>The very rehearſall of which reaſons is anſwer ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, he being notable to proue, any of theis aſſertions, but either by the Aſſumption it ſelfe, that they are brought to proue or one by another circularly; Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I affirme.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That ther is no ordinary Miniſteriall office that Chriſt hath giuen vnto his Church, for the worke of his Miniſtery, but our Miniſters either haue or by our lawes ought to haue the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That it is a Miniſtery as oppoſite for the ſubſtaunce therof, to the Miniſtery of Popiſh, Prieſts, &amp; Deacons, as light is oppoſit to darkneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the Pope left not ſuch Prieſts, and Deacons as ours are, nor hath any ſuch in his Kingdome; But that our Prieſts and Deacons, haue bene vnder God and the Prince, the principall Perſons that haue driuen, the Pope and his Prieſts and Deacons, out of the Realme; That it is deviliſh for any to ſay that they are deviliſh except they can proue it by better reaſons. That they that haue the beſt gifts, doe not intice any to ſtolne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or hidden bread, or to vphould any Miſtery of
<pb facs="tcp:177068:29"/>iniquitie; Except the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and the true and onely meanes of ſalvation; bee the Miſtery of iniquitie.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That our Church Aſſemblies being ſuch as by the lawes of the land they ought to bee; are ſo far forth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the world, joyned together in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Goſpell, by the voluntary profeſſion of faith, &amp;c. and freed from Antichriſt, as is ſufficient to make them true viſible Churches of Chriſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that many things may bee wanting, to the full and deſired perfection of them. And I doubt not but wee ſhall bee far more able at any time by reaſon out of Gods worde, to proue theis points, then ever M. Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will bee to proue the contrary. And yet it were eaſie to proue any thing, by ſuch a jugling Method of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, as M. Iohnſon hath gotten; For hee can proue you the 1. Reaſon by the 2, the 2. by the 1. The 3. by the 1. and 2, the 1. and 2. by the 3. The 4. by the 1.2. &amp; 3. and every of them by the 4. and all 4. by that queſtion which here they are brought to proue.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:29"/>
                  <head>THE FIFT REASON. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>NOne may heare or haue any Spirituall communion with thoſe Miniſters, which Miniſter the holy things of God, and worke vpon the Conſciences of men, by vertue of a fals Spirituall calling.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such are the Miniſters of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>None may heare or haue any Spirituall communion with them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Argument which here hee brings againſt our Miniſtery, is the very ſame with the 2. For by <hi>a fals Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall calling,</hi> hee meanes a calling proceeding from <hi>the Apoſtaſie of Antichriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Prepoſition for brevitie ſake hee proues by fiue and thirtie places of Scripture: And yet who ſoeuer ſhall pleas to take the paines to examine them, ſhall finde, that nether ſeverally nor joyntly, they proue the ſame.</p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption wheron the whole weight of the controverſie, leaneth, hee proueth onely by the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, wherby hee proued the Aſſumption of the 2.
<pb facs="tcp:177068:30"/>Reaſon viz. <hi>Becauſe they doe it by vertue of their Miniſtery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved of their Prelats, from their Spirituall Authority, which is vſurped and Antichriſtian;</hi> And this is all this witneſſe hath to ſay; and all the anſwer it needeth; Onely hee wandreth into certaine objections, and queries, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon ſome ſuppoſed defences of ſome of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; Vnto which I will (though I neede not) giue a breif anſwer from point to point.</p>
                     <q>Obj. <hi>Some ſay they preach not by vertue of their Miniſtery taken from the Prelats, but by vertue of ſome other calling and Authority.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> I knowe none hauing receaued ordination from the Prelats, that neede deny that they preach partly by vertue of the Miniſtery which they haue taken from them; Noe though they hould the calling of Prelates vnlawfull: For what is the Miniſtery which they haue taken from them, for the ſubſtance therof. But (after a triall of their gifts) a libertie, and leaue graunted vnto them to preach the worde of God, and adminiſter the Sacraments, in ſuch Congregations as they ſhall bee called vnto.</p>
                     <q>Obj. <hi>Why will ſuch ſeeme to renounce that calling, receaued of the Prelats, and yet blame vs for doing the like.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> They may acknowledge a further calling, then that of the Prelats, and yet not therin renounce the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling receaved from the Prelates, but rather ratifie the ſame; For the Prelats being learned divines, and having approued of their gifts, and by words, and letters Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall giuen, libertie to execute the Miniſtery of the Goſpell; they doe not therby thruſt them into a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, but they leaue them to bee further called or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:30"/>either by the people, or thoſe Patrons, vnto whoſe fidelitie the people haue committed this charge: And therfore this acknowledging of a further calling, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth nothing to the juſtification of the proude &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſchiſm of this Perſons.</p>
                     <q>Obj. <hi>If they preach by virtue of another calling how then ſtande they Miniſters of that Church wher noe other is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed, and how impoſe they themſelues vpon any of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe Aſsemblies, ſeing the lawes of the land allow onely the Prelacie, Prieſthood, and Deaconry a foreſaide,</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though this ſhould be graunted (which hee in his ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſimplicitie doth ſuppoſe) that ſome amongſt vs, hauing bene ordained by the Prelates did exerciſe our Miniſtery, by virtue of another calling, and though the law of the land, alow noe other, yet (eſpecially ſo long as they are permitted to execute their Miniſtery by thoſe in Authority, though it bee by virtue of another calling) they are to bee reputed Miniſters of that Church, that hath vſe of their Miniſtery.</p>
                     <q>Obj. <hi>How alſo herein can they avoide to bee both intruders and hipocrits, intruders in taking vpon themſelues a publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que office in that Church againſt the publique lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions therof, hipocrits, becauſe they pretend in ſhew one thing to the Prince, and State, and yet performe another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> All theis inferences are vpon a fals ſuppoſition; yet if there were any ſuch Perſons, they could noe more therin bee ſaid to bee intruders, and hipocrits then they of the Seperation are; For though the publique lawes ſhould bee againſt any other calling, yet ſo long as they take an office by a good calling, they cannot bee ſaid to
<pb facs="tcp:177068:31"/>intrude themſelues. Nether doe any ſuch amongſt vs (if ther bee any ſuch) pretend in ſhew any more then they doe indeed performe, for ſo far forth as any differ in iudgement from the publique lawes, of the State, they are ready to profeſſe it, being called thervnto, and they practis onely that, which they iudge lawfull, being as ready, as any of the ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuffer, rather then prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis approue, or aſſent vnto any thing, which they judge vnlawfull, and vnwarrantable.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>But ſuppoſe they had ſome other lawfull calling yet they alſo retaining this vnlawfull calling of the Prelats this were but to halt betweene two opinions, and to ſet their threſhould by Gods threſhoulds and their poſts by Gods poſts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> How can ſuch bee ſaid to retaine the vnlawfull calling of the Prelats, which proteſt againſt the ſame, &amp; profeſſe that they preach not by that, but by another calling? But if ther bee any ſuch, that exerciſe their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery by another calling beſids that of the Prelats, they therin refuſe; obeidience, and conformitie to what ſoever in the Prelats calling they judge vnlawfull, and ſo doe not joyne an vnlawfull and a lawfull calling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but reject the corruptions, retaine the good, and ſupplie the defect with another calling; and this is the worſte that can bee made of it; But this is not to joyne mans Treſhoulds to Gods, &amp;c. but clean contrary, to ſeperate them, as much as may bee; And how can they bee ſaide to halt betweene two opinions, when ſo far onely as the truth (in their iudgement and opinion) is eſtabliſhed by publique lawes they imbrace it, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging their ſubjection to the ſame lawes, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, wher they judge that the law ſwerves from the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:31"/>truth, they take another courſe, But ſtill hee begs this, (which is the maine controverſie) that our Miniſters haue receaued an vnlawfull calling from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates.</p>
                     <p>In the next place hee labors to proue by reaſons <hi>that howſoever ſome pretend another calling, yet it is evident, that the execute all the duties of their Miniſteries, by virtue of their calling taken from their Prelats;</hi> But what of that; This will ſtand him in noe ſteed, vnleſſe it bee given him of almes. <hi>That every Miniſtery executed by virtue of a calling taken from the Prelats, is an vnlawfull and an Antichriſtian Miniſterie;</hi> For proue it hee cannot, And if wee ſhould, except this alſo bee given him, <hi>That our Miniſtery is executed ONLY by virtue of a calling taken from the Prelats;</hi> and not by any other power, or virtue beſids, taken either from God or man. But let vs ſee his reaſons.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1. They cannot ſtand publique Miniſters except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of the Prelats the Prieſthood and Deaconry a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2. They are excommunicated</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>if they affirme that they whoe are made Biſhops, Deacons, and Prieſts, are not lawfully made, vntill thie haue ſome other calling.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3. The people haue not the liberty of the Churches of Chriſt nor power in this their eſtate to choſe and ſubmit vnto the true and lawfull Miniſtery appointed by Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4. Without and againſt the peoples conſent, they are by the Prelats a lone ſilenced, depriued, and degraded from exerciſiing any Miniſtery in thoſe Aſsemblies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theis reaſons doe not proue, That they exerciſe their miniſtery ONLY by virtue of a calling receaved fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:32"/>Prelats, and therfore whether true or fals are nothing to the purpoſe, and vnworthy any further Anſwer.</p>
                     <p>After this hee fetcheth another Rode out, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to proue, <hi>that our Miniſters ought not to ſuffer themſelues to bee ſilenced, and depoſed from their publique Miniſtery, no not by lawfull Magiſtrats,</hi> which is not onely fals and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; as ſhall appeare afterwarde, but idle and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to the preſent controverſie, for if it were true that Miniſters ought not to doe in this caſe, as ours doe; yet this doth not argue, any corruption in the calling of their Miniſtery, but a weackneſſe onely in the Perſons that execute it, in yealding further from their owne right, then they neede to doe; But let vs conſider the perticulers, that hee objecteth againſt our Miniſters in this reſpect.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>The Apoſtles being true Miniſters of Chriſt would not at the commandement of lawfull Magiſtrats, leaue to preach, much leſse ſhould true Miniſters, at the appointement of vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Prelats. Nether did the Apoſtles make, their imediate calling from God the ground of their refuſall, but this, That they ought to obey God rather then man, which is a duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of all Miniſters and Chriſtians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Wher hee diſtinguiſheth between ſilencing, &amp; depriving, by Prelats and lawfull Magiſtrats, it is in our caſe, wher the Prelats doe it by Authority, and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from lawfull Magiſtrats; a diſtinction without a difference. 2. Though the Apoſtles did not aſſigne, their imidiate calling from God, as the ground of their refuſall, in ſo many letters, and ſillables, yet that which they doe aſſigne, is by implication, and in effect the ſame with it; for it is as much as if they had ſaid; God himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:177068:32"/>hath impoſed this calling vpon vs, and not man; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore except wee ſhould rather obey man, then God, wee may not forbeare, this office, which hee hath impoſed vpon vs. For oppoſing the obeidience of God to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beidience of man, hee therin pleads a calling from God; and not from man: otherwiſe if they had receaved a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from man, there had bene incongruitie in the anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, conſidering that in common ſence and reaſon, they ought ſo far forth to obey men, forbidding them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe a calling, as they exerciſe the ſame by virtue of that calling els by this reaſon, A Miniſter ſhould not ceas to preach, vpon the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Church, that hath choſen him, but ſhould be bound to giue them alſo the ſame anſwer which they Apoſtles gaue, which were abſurd. So that by this groſſe conceit of M. Iohnſons, their ſhould bee no power, in any ſort of men whomſoever, to depoſe a Miniſter from his Miniſtery, but that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding any comandement: of Church or State the Miniſter is to continue in his Miniſtery. But for the further anſwer of this his ignorant conceit plainly tending to ſedition, wee are to know; That though the Apoſtles, Prophets, and Euangeliſts, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched publiquely where they were not hindred by open violence, And did not, nor might not leaue their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery vpon any humain Authoritie and commandement whatſoever; becauſe they did not enter into or exerciſe the ſame, vpon the will, and pleaſure of any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; yet they never erected and planted <hi>publique</hi> Churches and Miniſteries in the face of the Magiſtrate, whether they would or noe, or in diſpite of them. But ſuch in reſpect of the eye of the Magiſtrat, were as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb facs="tcp:177068:33"/>and inviſible as might bee: Neither were ſome of the Apoſtles onely forbidden, ſo as others ſhould bee ſuffered to preach the ſame Ghoſpel in their places: but the vtter aboliſhing of Chriſtian Religion was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly intended in the ſilencing of them. But our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches wherof wee are Miniſters, are noe private &amp; ſecreat Aſſemblies, ſuch as hide themſelues from the face of a perſecuting Magiſtrat, and State. But are publique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their worſhip, &amp; doing their religion in the face of the Magiſtrate and State, yea and by his contenance, authoritie and protection; And wee are ſet over thoſe Churches, not onely by a calling of our people, but alſo by the authoritie of the Magiſtrate who hath an armed power to hinder any ſuch publique Action: who is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alſo to permitte and maintaine other true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel in thoſe places where hee forbiddeth ſome. If therfore after our publique calling, to Miniſter to ſuch a knowne and publique Church, but by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat alſo, The Magiſtrate ſhall haue matter againſt vs, (whether juſt or injuſt it skilleth not) and ſhall in that regard forbid vs to Miniſter to our Church. I ſee not by what warrant in Gods word, wee ſhould thinke our ſelues bounde not withſtanding to exerciſe our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ſtill; Except wee ſhould thinke ſuch a law of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to ly vpon vs, that wee ſhould judge our ſelues bound, to run vpon the ſword point of the Magiſtrate or to oppoſe ſword to ſworde. It being not the vſe of the higher powers, in ſuch caſes nakedly to forbid, but to ſet a ſword to the breaſt, therby to force them, which ſhall refuſe. And ſuppoſe the Magiſtrate ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:177068:33"/>doe it injuſtly, and againſt the will of the Church, and ſhould therin ſinne; yet doth not the Church, in that regard ceas to bee a Church, nor ought ſhee therin to reſiſt the will of the Magiſtrate; Nether doth ſhee ſtand bound in regard of her affection to her Miniſter (how great and deſerved ſoever) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive her ſelfe of the protection of the Magiſtrat, by leauing her publique ſtanding to follow her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery in private and the darke; refuſing the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all other publique Miniſtery, which with the leaue and liking of the Magiſtrate ſhee may injoy; Nether doe I knowe what warrant any ordinarie Miniſter hath by Gods worde in ſuch a Caſe ſo to draw any ſuch Church or people to his private Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, that therby they ſhould hazzard their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtate and quiet in the Common wealth wher they liue, when in ſome competent Meaſure they may publiquely, with the grace and fauours of the Magiſtrat, inioy the ordinarie meanes of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, by another, (and except hee haue a calling to Miniſter to ſome other Church) to bee content to live as a private member, till it ſhould pleaſe God to reconcile the Magiſtrate vnto him, and ſo call him againe to his owne Church, laboring in meane while, privately vpon perticuler occaſions offred, to ſtrengthen and cofirme, in the wayes of God thoſe people that are deprived of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique labours, and I take it to bee the dutie, of the people in ſuch a caſe, if they will approue
<pb facs="tcp:177068:34"/>themſelues, faithfull Chriſtians, and good Subjects, ſo to ſubmit to the Miniſtery of another, as that by prayer and all other good dutifull and loyall meanes, they may doe their beſt indevour to obtaine him of whom againſt their will, they haue bene deprived and ſtill to affect and loue him as their Paſtor. Now if the people doe thus, then is that Miniſter called to bee ſilent not onely by the Magiſtrate, but by them alſo, though with much greife.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>It is the dutie of all Miniſters, and Chriſtians as will as Apoſtles, to obey God, and not man, when man forbiddeth that which God commandeth, or commandeth that which God forbiddeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, but God noe wher that I can find, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth either a Miniſter to Miniſter publiquely in a publique Church maintained by the Magiſtrate, againſt the will, and in deſpite of the Magiſtrate, noe more then againſt the will and in deſpite of the Church it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Vriah at the commaundement of the King made an Alter after the faſhion of that of Damaſcus but therin ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though hee offred theron ſuch burnt-offrings as God had appointed; much leſse may the Miniſtery vnder the Goſpell, bee framed after any nue manner deviſed by man leaſt of all after Antichriſt, though in that Miniſtery many doctrines of the Goſpell bee taught, and ſuch Sacraments adminiſtred as God hath ordained.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Example of Vriah the Prieſt is altogether impertinent, vnto that which goeth before. It being one thing vpon the commaundement of the Magiſtrate to forbeare the publique exerciſe of a true Miniſtery, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing vpon his commaundement to frame a nue
<pb facs="tcp:177068:34"/>Miniſtery after a nue manner devized by man or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
                     <p>After this hee runs out of his way againe to ſatisfie an objection, that hee had propounded and indevoured (as far as his learning would giue him leaue) to anſwer before; And which doth nothing at all depend vpon any thing that goeth before in this Argument, wherin hee reſembles ſome wanton Curs, that takes delight to turne round about to catch their owne tailes; But let vs ſee what it is hee ſaith.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Here againe concerning ſuch as plead that they teach the truth, and many excellent points of Doctrine. It is to bee obſerved, that yet none may therfore heare their Miniſtery vnder Coler of learning the truth becauſe in yealding to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue and heare it from Antichriſts Miniſtery, They defile the Temple of God, and become the Subjects of Antichriſt, pag. 75.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wher hee againe, taketh it as matter that muſt whether wee will or noe, bee graunted vnto him, <hi>That our Miniſtery is Antichriſts Miniſtery,</hi> which needs noe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer then before, yet thus much further. 1. That noe Miniſtery whatſoever (ſo far forth as it teacheth the truth of Chriſt eſpecially a truth oppoſite to the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Antichriſt) is the Miniſtery of Antichriſt; And tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe which ſhall ſubmit and ſubject themſelues vnto any Miniſtery whatſoever, onely ſo far forth as they Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and teach ſuch truth, cannot therin bee ſaid to defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le the Temple of God, or to bee Subjects of Antichriſt, but bee obedient to Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Our Miniſtery in divers Congregations of the land at the leaſt, Teach not onely <hi>many excellent points of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin.</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:35"/>But ſo much doctrine as is ſufficient to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that beleeueth the ſame; even all the maine fundamentall points of Salvation clearly ſet downe in Gods word; yea and for ought any can proue to the countrary. All other leſſe neceſſary points, ſo far forth, as God hath revealed, and convinced their conſciences of the truth of them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Thoſe amongſt vs who make conſcience of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our Miniſtery, doe not heare them <hi>vnder a Colour</hi> of learning the truth, but onely to this very end, and purpoſe, that they <hi>might</hi> learne the truth, and therin the true way of ſerving and worſhipping God according to his owne will.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>And not to ſpeake of the many errors &amp; falſhoods which they alſo teach, it is no nue thing that the Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſhould in diuers things teach and bring the truth with them, for when Sathan cannot by falſhood vtter his wares, ordinaunces, Miniſtery worſhip, hee will bee glad to vtter the ſame by teaching the truth. pag. 75.76.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Our Errors whether for weight or member, or qualitie, are not ſuch, ſo great, ſo many, but they may be fall vnto true Chriſtians, whether Miniſters or people, yea (as M. Iohnſon well knoweth) many of the Martyrs of Ieſus Chriſt, haue liued and died, in more and greater Errors of the ſame kinde, and therfore well may hee paſſe by this point. This is but a peece of his ſimple the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricke, careleſly to ſeeme to paſſe by that which hee cannot proue. For how many Errors, can hee name or number, that hee is able to juſtify to be taught in the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies? what one truth of Religion can hee name, that is not or hath not bene
<pb facs="tcp:177068:35"/>(when juſt occaſion hath bene offred) taught by ſome of our Miniſters? I am not ignorant that in his treatiſes againſt M. A. H. and M. H. I. hee muſtreth a whole troup of pretended Errors, but ſuppoſe them to bee ſo many deſtinct Errors, how doth hee proue they are taught in our Miniſtery or that they are required by law to bee taught? Ther is indeed a Conformitie and Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required to ſome of them, and a Canon that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that the late Canons bee reade in Churches ſome times in the yeare, as alſo that the booke of Articles bee read at the firſt entrance vpon an Eccleſiaſtical Church, with a teſtification of aſſent vnto it: But is this Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially to teach the Errors contained in the ſaid bookes? May not a man in the weackneſſe of his judgement, and in infirmitie at his firſt entrance into a calling, conforme and ſubſcribe vnto ſome things, not ſo warantable, and true, and yet not teach them for truths; yea may hee not, for all that teach doctrin in it ſelfe directly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thoſe vntruths, yea and yet ſatisfie alſo the minde of the law, which being humaine, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not alwaies perfect, may commaunde that very truth to bee taught, which being thorowly followed, will deſtroy ſome vntruths, which the ſame law alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires? Further it is one thing to reade the Canons to the people, therby to declare vnto them what is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at their hands, by their Governors, another thing to teach, and juſtifie the Errors countained in them, and to teſtifie an aſſent vnto ſome Errors, is not Miniſterially to inſtruct the people in thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:36"/> 2. Though <hi>it bee noe nue thing that the Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſhould in divers things bring the truth with them;</hi> Yet this is a nue thing and never hard of before, That the Miniſters of Antichriſt, ſhould teach the wholl truth of Chriſt Ieſus for the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof. That they ſhould oppoſe directly and zealouſly againſt the maine, and foundamentall doctrins of Antichriſt; That they ſhould profeſſe him to bee Antichriſt, and that man of ſinne, and to the ſheeding of their blood, ſhould exerciſe their Miniſtery againſt Antichriſt and his kingdome, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting againſt him and his Service, were it not nue ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that a man ſhould bee counted a true Subject vnto a Prince, then when hee doth openly proteſt againſt him. Counting him a vſurping Tirant, and imploying all the wit power and ſtrength hee hath againſt him? ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Antichriſt are our Miniſters, or by the lawes ſuch they ought to bee. Could hee bee ſaid to bee a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, that yealding to ſome externall kites, and profeſſing ſome doctrines of Chriſtian faith, doth not withſtanding, directly, openly and profeſſedly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſt and his Seruice, and profeſſe himſelfe to bee an enemie to him, and his Kingdome, If it hould not in the one, it is not both a nue and ſtrang thing that it ſhould hould in the other.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. M. Iohnſon out of his knowledge muſt teach vs; how Sathan can be ſaid, by teaching the truth to vtter his owne Miniſtery, or worſhip, or how a Sathanicall Miniſtery can be vttered when in and by the Miniſtery, nothing but the truth of Chriſt is adminiſtred; what is the Miniſtery of Sathan but the Miniſtery of Error? how can the Miniſtery of Error bee vttered by teaching
<pb facs="tcp:177068:36"/>the Truth? or how can a Miniſtery be ſaid to be vttered, by a truth, when it is the Miniſtery it ſelfe that vttereth the truth, Surely noe more then a Marchandize can bee ſaid to bee vttered by ſelling of wares, and were it not a wonder, if a man ſhould vtter his bad Marchandice, by ſelling good &amp; ſound wares? Sathan and Antichriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed together with ſome truths, ſeeke to vtter much falſhoode, which otherwiſe (they knowe) would not be receaued: And many of our Miniſters are content to yeald to ſome things which they judge not ſo counve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient (if it did otherwiſe ſome good to the State) to the end they may vtter the truth. But that like Antichriſt and Sathan our Miniſters ſhould propound this vnto themſelues, to teach ſome truths to this end that they might, therby vtter falſhood and lies, fals Miniſteries &amp; worſhips is a Malitious imputation, and can never bee juſtified.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Beza ſaith, Though Antichriſt teach the truth (which ſometimes hee doth) to the end hee may more eaſily ſeduce to beleeue his lies, yet wee are to ſtoppe our eares againſt him, leaſt vnder his pretence, wee bee deceaved by him. pag. 76.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Well, but it is yet to proue, That our Miniſters are Antichriſts, and that they teach the truth to any ſuch wicked intent; the contrary is manifeſt, when many of them in regard of the times, are countent, to yealde to ſome colourable vntruths, that they might therby pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe libertie vnto themſelues, to aduance the truth of Chriſt, They yeald to ſome things in appearance Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, that they might with more libertie fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Who knoweth not that Antichriſt and his Miniſters
<pb facs="tcp:177068:37"/>are hipocriticall frends to Chriſt vnder the name of Chriſt fighting againſt him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> But who knoweth not that our Miniſters, if they bee ſuch as our lawes require them to bee, are ſworn e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to Antichriſt, and in the name of Chriſt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome of Antichriſts owne Rites doe fight againſt him and reſiſt him vnto blood; And who knoweth not, that many of them haue died for Chriſt at the foot of Antichriſt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE SIXT ARGVMENT.</head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF the preſent Miniſtery of the Church of Englande bee a ſtrange Miniſtery, then is it not lawfull in the worſhip of God, to heare it, or haue any Spirituall communion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But ſuch is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of England.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is not lawfull in the worſhip of God to heare it, or haue any Spirituall Communion therwith.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is manifeſt, for a ſtrange Miniſtery is that which is not by the law ordained, and giuen for that worke, as themſelues here to fore haue publiſhed, and as is proued in the firſt Reaſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Reaſon differreth not in ſubſtance from divers of the former, for what is it to bee a ſtrang Miniſtery, but to be a Miniſtery that is not ſet by Chriſt in his Church
<pb facs="tcp:177068:37"/>which is his 1. Reaſon. But to bee a Miniſtery which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riveth not the power and function from Chriſt, which is his 4. Reaſon. But to bee a Miniſtery that worketh v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mens conſciences by virtue of a fals Spirituall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling which is his 5. Reaſon. Might hee not with as greate facility out of this method of reaſoning haue brought forth 7000. Reaſons as theis ſeaven. But how doth hee proue the Aſſumption of his reaſon? by ſending vs back againe (as you may ſee) to the firſt Reaſon. So that all the reaſon of this Reaſon is borrowed from the 1. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and is anſwered all ready in the Anſwer therof.</p>
                     <p>But before hee paſſeth to the next reaſon, hee runs out after the wonted faſhion, into an idle diſcours, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all appertaining to the Argument in hand, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in ſome idle obſervations vpon the Story of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan, and Abiram, &amp; alſo of Naaman, falſly Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applied vnto our Church Aſſemblies &amp; Miniſtery. For hee taking it as graunted, or as a thing that could not be denied him, That our Miniſtery is Antichriſtian, &amp; that our worſhip is Idolatry, hee makes our Miniſters, &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple even the beſt of them wors then Corah, Dathan, &amp; Abiram and them which were of their conſpiracy, and our Aſſemblies and worſhip as bad as the Temple of Rimmon, and the idolatry therin performed. And wher hee brings the example of Naaman, as brought by ſome of vs to juſtifie our joining with our Church Aſſemblies I perſuade my ſelfe he doth againſt the knowledge and light of his owne conſcience bely vs; &amp; that ther cannot be one of vs brought forth, that ever made this plea; we hould it as vnlawful (as themſelues) outwardly &amp; but in appearance to joyne with Idolators, in their Idolatry: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:177068:38"/>wee ſee noe warrant why for every perticuler Act, that in a large ſence is Idolatrous, adjoined to Gods true worſhip, wee ſhould forbeare our preſence, at the true worſhip it ſelfe. Or that our preſence, for the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſake alone, ſhould in reſpect of ſome point of falſe worſhip thervnto a nexed bee (as hee ſpeaketh) <hi>the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our bodies to a ſtrang worſhip.</hi> Eſpecially when wee are not perticuler Actors in it, but onely preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding it with greife, and ſuffering it in others for the true worſhip ſake vnto which it is adjoined, If this ſhould bee held vnlawfull; then can noe man preſent himſelf with a good conſcience, at any publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God wherſoever. Becauſe (except it ſhould be ſtinted and preſcribed, which M. Iohnſon holds to bee a fals worſhip) hee can haue noe aſſeurance, but that ſome errors in matter or forme will bee committed; yea if hee bee a man of vnderſtanding, and learning, hee may preſume in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, that in the publique worſhip, ſome error or other in matter or forme, greater or leſſer will bee committed, before which he muſt preſent himſelfe. But what? were the Iewiſh Sinagoges in Chriſts time free from all parts of fals worſhip? the Scripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the contrary. Did they when Chriſt came into them, for beare their Aſſemblies? The Scripture confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the contrary, was Chriſt preſence then (as heere he ſaith our preſence is) <hi>a very bowing downe vnto them? was hee alſo therin an vnconſcionable diſsembler.</hi> Did hee therin <hi>imbrace the boſome of Strangers? breake his couenant, goe a whoreing with the inventions of man.</hi> For (ſuch fiere as this hee ſpits at vs) if not, why ſhould it bee ſuch a ſin in vs? who haue not ſuch eyes to pearce into the impiety of mans traditions, as our Saviour had.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:38"/>
                  <head>THE SEAVENTH Reaſon. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF the preſent Miniſtery of the Church of Englande bee not from Heaven, but of men, then is it not lawfull in the worſhip of God to heare or haue any Spirituall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion therwith.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi> Ergo, <hi>It is not lawfull in the worſhip of God to haue any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall communion therwith.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Aſsumption is evident, becauſe God hath not appointed the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies, but man, as appeares by their booke or ordination, And if they will ſay the contrary, let themſhew their callings out of the word of God.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Reaſon is the very ſame with the 4.5. and 6. and hath noe ground, or profe but from them: And therfore is Anſwered alſo in the Anſwer of them. And this may bee ſufficient to ſhew, that our Miniſtery is from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, when ſo malitious, and excerciſed an Adverſary whoſe whole Religion ſeemes to lie in oppoſing to our Miniſtery, can ſay noe more againſt it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:39"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SORT OF REASONS TAKEN AS is pretended forth of our owne Writers. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FIRST ARGVMENT TAKEN from the twelue Arguments. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>AL will-worſhip is Sinne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To heare or communicate with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande, in Church Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in manner and forme preſcribed, is a will-worſhip.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore to heare or communicate with that Miniſtery is Sinne.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Sillogiſme is Sophiſticall, conſiſting plainely of foure termes, Except hee make his concluſion this. <hi>Ther fore to heare or communicate with that Miniſtery in manner
<pb facs="tcp:177068:39"/>and forme preſcribed is a Sinne.</hi> For the third Argument being <hi>wil-worſhip.</hi> Al the other terms they being no parts therof, muſt bee in the concluſion: If ſo bee the ſillogiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me bee true as every Sophoming boy, in the vniverſitie knoweth: And therfore hee muſt either exclude them out of the Aſſumption, or include them in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which hee cannot doe, it being his intent, by theis Arguments to proue it a ſinne to communicate ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with not onely <hi>in manner or forme preſcribed,</hi> but any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, And therfore hee Sophiſtically, or rather in ignorant and witleſſe ſimplicity, concluds a generall from a Speciall thus,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>It is a will-worſhip to communicate with our Miniſtery in manner and forme preſcribed.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Therfore it is a ſinne to communicate therwith whether in manner or forme preſcribed or any other way.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wheras a Childe may knowe this, That an Action donne in ſome manner and forme preſcribed may bee a will-worſhip and a ſinne, which donne otherwiſe may bee true worſhip; A man may therfore (if neede bee) graunt both his premiſes and deny his concluſion. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will it help him, that the Author of the 12. Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, concluded againſt the Ceremonies, in the ſame forme of words, that hee doth here againſt the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, It being plain by the ſcope of his wholl diſputation, That though hee do not expreſſe thoſe words <hi>in manner and forme preſcribed,</hi> in the concluſion; That yet hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth them, It being not his purpoſe to diſpute abſolutely againſt all vſe of them, but againſt the vſe of them, in that manner and forme that they are preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:40"/>
                     <p> But whatſoever his Concluſion is, The Aſſumption is fals, yea though it ſhould bee graunted that in our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery ther is ſome will-worſhip performed; yet let vs ſee how hee proues the Aſſumption.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>All parts of divine worſhip and Service impoſed onely by the will and pleaſure of man vpon the Communicants in divine ſervice and that of neceſsitie to bee donne, is will-worſhip.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But to heare and Communicate, with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Eugland, in Church Service in manner and forme preſcribed, are ſuch parts of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as is a foreſaid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To heare and Communicate with the preſent Miniſtery of the Church Aſſemblies of England in manner and forme preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed is a will-worſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Propoſition is taken forth of the 12. Argumentes and therfore needs noe Anſwer.</p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption is fals, But hee proueth it thus,
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Man impoſeth this Miniſtery vpon man, and God in his word hath not appointed theſe offices and Callings, Nether required any to communicate with them in Church Service in manner and forme preſcribed.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>And 2. the people ſtand bound to heare, and communicate with them vpon paine of Suſpenſion, deprivation, &amp;c. and God muſt haue noe ſolemne worſhip in England except it be with communion to the ſame.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Ergo, <hi>To heare and communicate with the preſent Miniſtery,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:40"/>&amp;c. is a part of divine worſhip impoſed as a fore ſaide.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt part of the Anticedent is fals and is not proued by any ground taken from the 12. Arguments, for not man onely, but God alſo hath impoſed this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and hath appointed for the ſubſtance therof their offices &amp; Callings of the Miniſters of our Church Aſſemblies; And hath required vs to communicate with them in Church Service, in that forme and manner, which the law in the true meaning therof, preſcribes, &amp; which many at the leaſt doe practis.</p>
                     <p>Nether doth the conſequent follow vpon the ſecond part of the Antecedent, for though humaine lawes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der never ſo great puniſhments, ſhould bind vs to never ſo great corruptions in Gods Service; yet ſo lang as wee doe not actually communicate in thoſe corruptions, but onely in the true parts of Gods worſhip, our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating is never the wors; for the ſaid lawes of men, but rather the better. Nether doe wee herein ſtand more bound, then M. Iohnſon and his people doe, when they are in theis dominions: So that it makes as much againſt communicating with their Miniſtery as ours: Though therfore (as the Author of the 12. Arguments hath in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>devoured to proue) the Ceremonies in Controverſie ſhould be held to be a will-worſhip, and therfore a ſin to vſe them in Gods worſhip, yet it followeth not, by the ſame Argument that it is a ſinne, to communicate with the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies, noe though it ſhould vſe the ſaid Ceremonies, much leſſe, wher and when it vſeth them not, as in ſome places, or at ſome times it doth not, nether is it by law required ſo to doe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:41"/>
                  <head>THE SECOND REASON taken from the twelue Arguments. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IT is a ſinne againſt God for Chriſtians to pertake with the Miniſtery of ſuch, as accounting thomſelues to bee Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Ieſus Chriſt, yet doe in the execution of their Miniſtery giue ſpeciall honor to Antichriſt, and his officers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Miniſtery of the Church of England is ſuch.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is a ſinne for Chriſtians to pertake therwith.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Firſt I deny the Propoſition, The true and beſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ieſus Chriſt, that ever were or ſhall bee ſince the Apoſtles, may in their ignorance, or weacknes, do ſome act in their Miniſtry, that may bring ſome ſpeciall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to Antichriſt, and yet Chriſtians may lawfully, and without ſinne pertake with ſuch in their Miniſtery. It being not neceſſary, that who ſoever pertaketh, with a
<pb facs="tcp:177068:41"/>Miniſtery ſhould pertake alſo with the accidentall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions therof.</p>
                     <p>Hee tels vs like a bould and blind biard. <hi>That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is manifeſt and clear to any that haue an ey of Reaſon, and any light of divinitie ſhining in it.</hi> And yet it hath not ſo much as any colour of truth, but in the eyes of ſuch owles and bats as himſelfe is;
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> The Propoſition in the twelue Arguments vnto which hee would equall and paralel his, is this, <hi>It is a ſinne againſt God, for him that is by way of excellency a Servant of Ieſus Chriſt (without a preciſe and directe warrant from him at any time eſpecially in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne worſhip of God) to give ſpeciall honour to Antichriſt and his members;</hi> What? muſt it needs follow vpon this, That it is a ſinne to pertake any manner of way with ſuch a ones Miniſtery, as ſhall in any meaſure commit ſuch a ſinne? muſt the joining with them in any other parts of their Miniſtery needs bee a communicating with them in this ſinne? Hee bids vs <hi>ſee for this 2. Cor. 6.14.17. Rev. 18.4.</hi> but what is this to the twelue Arguments, from which hee ſaith this reaſon is taken? And to what end ſhould wee ſee thoſe places, except hee had firſt made vs to ſee, That our Miniſters in their Miniſtery are Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Belials. That their Miniſtery for the ſubſtance therof is <hi>vnrighteouſnes</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> That the God wee ſerued in our Miniſtery is an Idoll, That our Aſſemblies are Babylon. And all this becauſe ſome thing happily is donne, by our Miniſters, which (and yet contrary to their intent) is ſome honour to Antichriſt. For except all this bee graunted vnto him, theis Texts are of noe force to confirme the Prepoſition.</p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption is as fals as the Propoſition,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:42"/>Nether doth it follow from the Aſſumption, of that Argument of the 12. from which hee would ground it. For though it ſhould bee graunted, <hi>That to vſe the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in Controverſie in manner and forme preſcribed were to give ſpeciall honors to Antichriſt and his officers.</hi> Yet it doth not follow, That the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, are ſuch that in the execution of their Miniſtery giue ſpeciall honour to Antichriſt, and his officers. For ſome of our Miniſters, from whom hee ſeperateth, do not in the execution of their Miniſtery vſe the ſaid Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies at any time, Nether do any of our Miniſters at all times in the execution therof, vſe them, nether are required ſo to doe. The Aſſumption not-withſtanding hee proceedeth to proue thus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Such a Conformitie to Antichriſt and his officers as is not onely beſids the word of God, but in a ſpeciall manner derogatory to all reformed Churches that haue departed from the Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of Rome, is a ſpeciall honour to Antichriſt and his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the Execution of the Miniſtery of the Church of Englande is ſuch.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Execution of that Miniſtery in manner a foreſaid is to giue ſpeciall honour to Antichriſt and his officers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Propoſition is word for word in a manner taken out of the 12. Arguments. And therfore for this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie not to bee ſtood vpon, whether it be true, or fals.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:42"/>
                     <p> The Aſſumption is fals, and hath noe ground at all from the 12. Argumets. For though it ſhould be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>That to vſe the Ceremonies in Controverſie in divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſuch a Conformitie to Antichriſt, and his members,</hi> as is ſpecified in the Propoſition; yet noe man except hee haue ſome Crack in his braine, can from thence inferre, That the execution of our Miniſtery, is ſuch a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, eſpecially then when in the execution therof, they doe not vſe the ſaid Ceremonies, which none doe at all times, and ſome doe never.</p>
                     <p>Hee proceeds to proue the Aſſumption, not by any ground taken from the <hi>12. Arguments,</hi> but by ſome of the fragements of his owne former reaſonles reaſons, and therfore the maine iſſue of the Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, lying not vpon any thing, in the ſaid Arguments. This ſecond reaſon of his, cannot bee ſaid to bee taken from the 12. Arguments. And therfore they are noe wiſe guilty of his ſchiſme, nor doe any wayes herein this place, patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:43"/>
                  <head>THE THIRD REASON TAKEN OVT OF THE TWELVE Arguments the London Miniſters exceptions, and the Abridgement, &amp;c. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF ſuch bee the State of the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of England, as they are bound in their Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto ſuch things, as the vſing of them in Church Service, in manner and forme preſcribed, is a will-worſhip, a giving of ſpecially honour to Antichriſt and his members, a performing of honours more then Civill, even Religions, onely to a humaine power, a warranting of the like vſe of Iewiſh, Turkiſh, Paganiſh or Popiſh obſervations; a doing of Scyſmaticall Actions, an hauing of Spirituall Communion with Papiſts, in the Miſteries of their Idolatry, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Amingling of prophane things with divine, an vſing of vnlawfull things in divine worſhip; An adminiſtring of Sacraments, that are not of divine inſtitution. A ſolemne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of Speciall homage, to the Spirituall vſurped authoritie of Lord Biſhops, an vſing of humaine Traditions in Gods worſhip as neceſſary to ſalvation, an apparent meanes of the damnation of many Soules. An obſerving of a lieturgy
<pb facs="tcp:177068:43"/>which in the wholl matter, and forms therof, is too like vnto the maſse booke, &amp;c. Then is it not lawfull to communicate with the Miniſters in their Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But ſuch is the eſtate of the Miniſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is not lawfull to communicate with them therin.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>M. Iohnſon thinks ſurely, that in this Argument hee hath out of our owne writings, for ever diſgraced our Miniſtery; But whether here or in the Arguments fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he deale faithfully with our writers, I know not, his bad dealing in this kinde, wee haue diſcoured in part before, and doth moſt evidently appeare in one perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler following, wherein hee moſt ſhamfully and lewdly, as a man void of all common honeſty and grace, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Miniſters of Lincolne to affirme,
<note place="margin">See pag. 98.</note> 
                        <hi>That the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats are reveiled to bee great Antichriſts, and their Miniſtery, and conſtitution, to bee great troublers of the Church at this day, and that it cannot but bee very ſinfull and hurtfull, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine or communicate with them.</hi> The Devill himſelfe would haue bene a ſhamed in this open manner to haue tould ſuch a ly, and therfore hee is to bee truſted, no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then hee is ſeene; And herein his lewdneſſe is the more to bee ſuſpected, That wher hee rehearſeth many harſh, bitter, and vnſauory ſpeaches againſt our Miniſtery and worſhip, as written by ſome of our ſelues, that retaine communion with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and worſhip of our Church Aſſemblies; Hee doth not quote the perticuler places, but onely refers
<pb facs="tcp:177068:44"/>vs to the Authors in generall, as though we had nothing els to doe, but to reede ouer wholl bookes to finde out his Allegations, or that wee muſt take them vpon his word to bee faithfully reported. But let vs ſuppoſe, that our men haue ſo written; yet ther is noe conſequent in the Propoſition: For what if our Miniſtery were bound to ſay Maſſe, to ſing Mattins. To worſhip the Virgin Mary. To acknowledge the Popes Supremacie, &amp;c. yet for all that it might bee lawfull to Communicate with our Miniſters, in their Miniſtery: Except that in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Miniſtery they ſubmitted vnto that which they were bound vnto. It being one thing, to bee bound, and another thing to fulfill the bonde; he might contrarily with as much witt and vnderſtanding haue reaſoned thus, <hi>If this bee the eſtate of the Miniſtery of the Church Aſſemblies of Rome, that they are bound in their admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, to the renouncing of Antichriſt, and all his Idolatry, offices, and will-worſhip; to conforme onely, in their Miniſtery to the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and to ſuch or dinances as are agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſame, then it is lawfull to communicate with them in their Miniſtery and worſhip.</hi> M. Iohnſon would quickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the inconſequence of this Propoſition; And why? becauſe in the execution of their Miniſtery, they fulfill not this bound; And yet hee cannot deny, but that they are, by a ſtranger bond, even a divine bond, bounde vnto this, then our Miniſters to the contrary.</p>
                     <p>The conſequent hee ſaith is proued by the <hi>Miniſters of Lincolneſhire, Abridgement pag. 17.</hi> But to paſſe by his depraving of them before touched, noe ſuch matter can bee concluded from the words, which hee here citeth, yea though hee had dealt faith-fully in the citation of
<pb facs="tcp:177068:44"/>them. For though it ſhould bee graunted that ſome act of ſpirituall fornication ſhould bee donne in our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,
<q>That wee are to ſeperate from Idolators and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians, and to bee as vnlike them as may bee, in their religious obſervations, Though God doe beare a dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Idolatry, and all the Inticements therof, as vnto ſpeciall whoredome. Though wee ought to bee a ſhamed of the monuments of Idolatry, and caſt them away with deteſtation. Though wee ſhould bee in ſome danger by them to bee corrupted in Religion, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming vnto Idolators in their Miniſtery and worſhip. Though keeping communion with ſuch Miniſters ſhould be a ſpeciall meanes to harden them in their ſins. Though the Prelats were revealed to bee great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts. Though the Godly learned haue conſtantly taught, that Chriſtians are bound to forſake and caſt of the Miniſtration, Ceremonies, and religious cuſtomes of Pagan, Iewes, Antichriſtian Idolators, and Hereticks, and carefully to ſhum all conformity with them therin;</q> Yet it doth not therupon follow, <hi>That if the Miniſters of our Church Aſsemblies bee bound as a foreſaid, that then it is not lawfull to communicate with them in their Miniſtery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>M. Iohnſon therfore muſt bee put to this paines, To proue this conſequent.</p>
                     <p>For further profe of the former conſequent, he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſix Reaſons more out of his owne ould and fuſty horn of ſtore which proue the conſequent juſt a <hi>baculo ad augulum.</hi> To which it ſhall bee needleſſe to giue aunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, they being profes clean beſids the purpoſe of theis reaſons, which is to juſtify their ſchiſme by grounds ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from our owne writings.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:45"/>
                     <p> The Conſequent then of the Propoſition being evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently fals, The Aſſumption though it ſhould haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much ground from our owne writings, wil ſtande him in noe ſtead.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FOVRTH REASON TAKEN OVT OF THE ADMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to the Parlament. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF the Offices of Arch Biſhops, Arch Deacons, Lord Biſhops, Suffraces, Parſons, Vicars, &amp;c. bee Antichriſtian and contrary to the Scriptures, then the people of God may not communicate with them in their Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Ergo,</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The firſt is true.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The later alſo.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Conſequent is fals, and hee goeth not about to proue it, by any thing taken out of our owne writings but by a ſtale profe that hath bene anſwered before; and therfore it requires noe anſwer, onely thus much of free bountie. That the offices of Arch Biſhops &amp;c. <hi>quatenes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> are not of the eſſence of the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies but meere Accidents.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:45"/>
                     <p> The Aſſumption therfore will ſtand him in noe ſteed whether it bee true or fals, and therfore I leaue it to their maintenance from whom hee ſaith hee borroweth it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE FIFT REASON TAKEN OVT OF THE offer of Conference. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF the Propoſitions propounded to bee maintained in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Conference bee true,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">To avoid te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes, I forbeare to ſet them downe as M <hi>Iohnſon</hi> hath done, but thou ſhalt diſcern what they are after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the Anſwer.</note> 
                           <hi>then is it not lawfull to heare or haue any ſpeciall Communion with the preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Church Aſsemblies of Englande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But thoſe Propoſitions are true.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Ergo,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is not lawfull to haue any Speciall Communion with the ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Conſequent is fals; &amp; doth not follow from the ſaid Propoſitions.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Though it ſhould be graunted, <hi>That all matters mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely Eccleſiaſticall, lawfully impoſed vpon any Church are ſuch as may bee concluded neceſſarily from the written word of God.</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:46"/>Yet in a true conſtituted Church ſome matters meerely Eccleſiaſticall may bee impoſed through humaine frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that cannot ſo bee concluded.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Though, <hi>all humaine ordinances vſed onely or ſpecially in Gods worſhip, whervnto they are not neceſsary of themſelues were ſimply vnlawfull.</hi> Yet is not every ſuch humaine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of that nature, that it maketh the Church and Miniſtery wher it is vſed, to bee a fals Church, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, much leſſe thoſe Churches, and that Miniſtery, wherin it is not vſed, but injoined onely.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Though it were generally graunted of all, <hi>That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true viſible Church of Chriſt is ſuch a Spirituall body politick as is ſpecially inſtituted by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles in the new Teſtament.</hi> Yet it will not thence follow, That thoſe Churches, and Miniſteries are not to bee communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withall, that haue any thing in or appertaining to the conſtitution therof not inſtituted by Chriſt; or that ſuch Churches are not true viſible Churches.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Though, <hi>every true viſible Church of Chriſt or ordinary Aſsemblie of the faithfull, hath by Chriſts ordinance power in it ſelfe immedialy vnder Chriſt, to elect and ordaine, deprive and depoſe, their Miniſters, and to execute all other Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures.</hi> Yet will it not follow from thence, That all they are fals Churches, and not to bee communicated with all. That doe not or by the lawes of man are not ſuffred to vſe that power, Nether is it ſure the meaning of them who offer the Conference, To maintaine, That they are no true viſible Churches of Chriſt that cannot vſe that power; but are therein ſubject to others; for one may by Chriſts ordinance haue a power to doe that which yet in regard of man he hath noe power to doe.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:46"/> 5. Though, <hi>the Paſtor of a perticuler congregation ſhould be yealded to bee the higheſt ordinary Eccleſiaſticall officer in any true conſtituted viſible Church of Chriſt.</hi> Yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it not hence bee concluded, That thoſe Paſtors are fals Paſtors, who are outwardly by mans lawes, ſubjected to a Superior Eccleſiaſtical officer. The Father ordinary is the higheſt officer in the family; yet if the Magiſtrate ſubject the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſome matters appertaining to the family to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Though therin it may bee hee may doe the father ſome wrong, yet doth not the father therby become a fals father, or the family a fals family. Admitte then that this prerogatiue due to Paſtors, to haue noe Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall officers ſuperior vnto them, yet is it not ſo eſſential vnto him, that without the Actuall vſe and poſſeſſion of it, hee cannot bee a true Paſtor; And yet take a true viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church in that ſence, which the officers of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference doe viz. for a perticuler ordinary Aſſembly or Congregation, And then in our owne Churches, The Paſtor is the higeſt, ther being noe Eccleſiaſticall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in any ſuch Churches, a boue him.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Graunt this, <hi>That it is the office of every true. Paſtor to teach and Governe Spiritually one Congregation immediately vnder Chriſt.</hi> Can it from hence bee concluded, That they are noe true Paſtors, which governe more congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations then one, or which are ſubject in ſome outward things to ſome others beſids Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Admit, <hi>That the offices of Provinciall and dioceſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were contrary to the word of God;</hi> muſt it needs ther v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon follow, That thoſe Miniſters, and Churches which are vnder them by the lawes of man, are fals: ſuch eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially who obey them onely in things which they judge
<pb facs="tcp:177068:47"/>honeſt, and lawfull, and who vnder this ſubjection doe no more then they would doe, if they were not ſubject at all vnto the Biſhops.</p>
                     <p>A man muſt therfore bring a better head, &amp; wit with him, then M. Iohnſons, That by the Propoſitions of the <hi>offer of Conference</hi> (how harſh ſoeuer they may ſeeme to bee) can conclude it vnlawfull to joine and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with our Church Aſſemblies.</p>
                     <p>For the profe of this conſequent he bringeth nothing out of our owne writings, but onely to giue his reader therby a vomit, ſome of his owne Coleworts, not twiſe, but twiſe twenty times ſodden; To which wee giue him leaue to looke an Anſwer, from ſome as idle headded as himſelfe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE SIXT ARGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT TAKEN OVT OF DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Treatiſes Anſwered.
<note place="margin">This Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition being a whol leaf in his booke. I forbeare any further anſer downe, there being in effect little difference in the matter from that which hee hath former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought.</note>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Ihon.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IF the is Aſsertious bee true, That that Church calling for which the Scripture giue noe expreſse warrant, is meerely vſurped, and vtterly vnlawfull, That as it is not lawfull to bring in any ſtrange doctrin, ſo is it not lawful, to teach the true doctrine vnder the name of any other function then is inſtituted by God, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177068:47"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But the aforeſaid Aſsertions are true.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therfore it is vnlawful to haue communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with that Miniſtery.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This Argument being a collection out of our writers doth not differ from the former; as himſelfe graunteth, and therfore needs noe further Anſwer.</p>
                     <p>The Conſequent is fals, and hee proues it not by any of our owne writers, as hee ought to doe, but ſtil brings vs profes out of his owne muſty Aumbry.</p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption therfore borrowed out of our owne writers, will doe him noe pleaſure.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>THE SEAVENTH REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON TAKEN OVT OF THE twelue Arguments viz. the tenth. <hi>EXAMINED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Fr. Iohn.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IT is a ſinne againſt Chriſt the ſole head of the Church, to haue ſpirituall communion with thoſe Miniſters, which in their Adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of divine things do either by word or deed ſolemly profeſse and yeald a ſpirituall homage to an vſurped ſpirituall Authoritie in the Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But ſo do the Miniſters of the Church Aſsemblies of England.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>It is a ſinne to haue communion with the ſame.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:48"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>The Propoſition is fals; And hath noe ground from that Propoſition in the 12. Arguments vnto which hee would match, and forth of which hee would draw it. The Propoſition there is this. <hi>It is a ſinne againſt Chriſt, the ſole head of the Church, for any one of his Miniſters, eſpecially in the adminiſtration of divine things, either by words or ſignes, ſolemly to profeſſe, and acknowledge, a ſpirituall homage to a v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped Sperituall authoritie in the Church.</hi> Can hee conclude his propoſition from this doth it hence follow, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Miniſters in their Miniſtery if they conforme do in ſome meaſure in infirmitie or ignorance commit ſome ſuch ſinne, That therfore it is a ſinne to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with them, in other divine things, wherin they doe not commit the ſame ſinne?</p>
                     <p>Hee tels vs, <hi>That the Propoſition may not bee gaine-ſaid,</hi> and why doth hee tell vs ſo? becauſe the Author of the 12. Arguments ſaith, <hi>his Propoſition may not bee denied.</hi> As though there were juſt the ſame reaſon for the one as is for the other; But why may not the Propoſition; <hi>Becauſe all Spirituall power vſurped over the Churches of God is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Authoritie, &amp; to communicate with thoſe Miniſters which Profeſſe Spirituall homage therunto, is to communicate which ſuch as profeſse Spirituall homage to Antichriſt, which muſt needs bee a ſinne againſt Chriſt the head of the Church.</hi> A deepe and learned Reaſon. It can bee no ſinne againſt Chriſt, to communicate with them, which in ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction profeſſe Spirituall homage to Antichriſt, except in their communion, they alſo profeſſe the ſame homa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, which like an ignorant diſputant, hee maketh noe
<pb facs="tcp:177068:48"/>queſtion of. As though to joine with one, that doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, in that which is good, is alwaies to joine with him in the evill, as though to joine with a glutton in eating neceſſary food, were to joine with him in his gluttony, or to joine with a blaſphemer, in the act of his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in reſcuing an inocent out of the hands of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, were to communicate with him in his blaſphemy; But herein hee propounds onely to play the Ape imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Author of the twelue Arguments, who ſaith his Propoſition may not bee gaine ſaid, <hi>Becauſe all Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Power vſurped over the Churches of God, is an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Authority, and to profeſse ſpirituall homage thervnto, is to profeſſe ſpirituall homage vnto Antichriſt, which muſt needs bee a ſinne.</hi> But what? is there no more Reaſon in this reaſon then in his? If this bee a good Argument to proue that Propoſition for which it is brought, muſt his Argument needs, bee as good to proue his propoſition? what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a ſinne <hi>to profeſse Speciall homage vnto Antichriſt</hi> muſt it needs alſo bee a ſinne, <hi>to communicate alſo with them, who do profeſse ſome homage vnto Antichriſt,</hi> what? to communicate with them in other matters?</p>
                     <p>The Aſſumption is as fals as the Propoſition, And hath noe ground for the <hi>twelue Arguments,</hi> for though it were graunted, <hi>That to vſe the controverted ceremonies in manner and forme preſcribed were even in the ſolemne worſhip of Chriſt by ſolemne ſignes to acknowledge a ſpirituall homage to a ſpirituall vſurped Authority of Arch Biſhops and Biſhops.</hi> Yet doth it not ther-from follow, That our Miniſters in the adminiſtration of divine things, doe the ſame; for none of our Miniſters do <hi>alwaies</hi> in the adminiſtration of divine things profeſſe any ſuch homage, and ſome do
<pb facs="tcp:177068:49"/>never profeſſe it. And thoſe who profeſſe it, when they doe profeſſe it, propound, and intend noe ſuch matter.</p>
                     <p>Hee proues the Aſſumption, Thus</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They preach the word and adminiſter the Sacraments by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their calling receaved from the Arch-Biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c.</hi> The vanity wherof hath bene ſufficiently ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed all-ready hee therin begging one of his ſtale rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and not borrowing any thing, from the twelue Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. That which followeth, wherby hee would proue, <hi>That the Authority of L. Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops is vſurped,</hi> which he makes the 2. parts of his Aſſumption; is altogether idle, and to noe purpoſe, and donne onely of malice to the Author of the twelue Arguments for otherwiſe, had hee intended herein the convincing of the ſaid Author, and of them which are of his minde, (which is the onely vſe of the later ſort of his reaſons, &amp; which can ſerve for noe other vſe) it had bene ſufficient to haue produced his Aſſertion without his profes; for that had bene enough to declare, The Authors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit.</p>
                     <p>Hee concludes crowing as if hee were ſome Cock of the game, that had picked out the eyes and broken the necks of al that haue bene ſet againſt him. <hi>And thus</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the cauſe is yealded by themſelues.</hi> And is it not (thinke wee) finely yealded? is it not a feild ſtoutly wonne, Is it any mervaille, that hee makes ſuch out cries againſt the wholl Chriſtian world, that will not follow ſuch a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                     <p>But I leaue him to his vaine conceits of his owne cauſe, Truſting that any ſober and judicious Chriſtian, will bee able to diſcerne, therin his fond and ignorant
<pb facs="tcp:177068:49"/>vanity. And wher as in the Anſwer of his Reaſons, I haue omitted to anſwer to many perticuler paſſages. All things conſidered I ſhall not neede to aske him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, I ſhould rather haue cauſe to expect thanks, if I had to deale with a reaſonable and good natured adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>REASONS OR ARGVMENTS, TENDING TO PROVE THAT IT IS A ſinne to ſeperate from the publique Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Church Aſſemblies of Englande.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>DIRECTLY CONTRARY TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IONHSONS OWNE Reaſons.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">AND VSVALLY IN THAT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard made in the ſame moode and figure.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The firſt Argument.</head>
                  <p>It is a ſinne to ſeperate from that Miniſtery which is
<pb facs="tcp:177068:50"/>ſet by Chriſt in his Church for the worke of his Miniſterie.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch is the Miniſtery of the Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of England.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it is a ſinne to ſeperate from it.</p>
                  <p>The profes which he bringeth to confirme the maine Propoſition of his firſt Reaſon, will ſerue to proue this.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Aſſumption may bee proued thus.</item>
                     <item>The Miniſtery of true Paſtors and Teachers is the Miniſtery which is ſet by Chriſt in his Church.</item>
                     <item>The Miniſtery aforeſaid is the Miniſtery of true Paſtors and Teachers.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is a Miniſtery ſet by Chriſt in his Church.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is his owne.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption I proue thus.</p>
                  <p>The Miniſtery which hath in it all things eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the office &amp; calling of true Paſtors &amp; Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers is the Miniſtery of true Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch is our Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it is the Miniſtery of true Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  <p>I think he is not ſo ſimple as to deny the Propoſition.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proued thus.</p>
                  <p>To haue ſuch gifts as Chriſt aſcended to heauen to giue for the worke of his Miniſtery. To bee out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly called to that worke by ſuch a Church as profeſſeth the fondamentall points of the Goſpell. To inſtruct the people committed to their Charge, in the doctrine of the law and Goſpell: To admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto them the holy Sacraments of Chriſt, And
<pb facs="tcp:177068:50"/>to bee their month in prayer vnto God; Are all things eſſentially appertaining to the office of true Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  <p>Such is the Miniſtery of our Aſſemblies.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it is the true Miniſtery of Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
                  <p>If hee deny the Propoſition, hee muſt ſhew, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters do eſſentially appartaine vnto their calling which yet hee hath not donne.</p>
                  <p>For confirmation of the Aſſumption it ſhall bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that wee can ſet forth vnto him, ſuch a Miniſtery in ſundry of our Church Aſſemblies, of which all theiſe points may bee truely verified, their conformitie to the State, and their ſinne therin (if any bee) not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond Argument.</head>
                  <p>The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies is not the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it is a ſinne to ſeperate from the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The conſequent muſt bee true vntill hee can bring forth any other exceptions againſt our Miniſtery then ſuch as appertaine to the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proued thus.</p>
                  <p>The Miniſtery of the Church Aſſemblies of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is of Prieſts and Deacons.</p>
                  <p>But the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies is not the Miniſtery of Prieſts and Deacons.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it is not the Miniſtery of Antichriſts Apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:51"/>
                  <p> The Propoſition is his owne.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption if I ſhould follow his learning, I might proue thus, The Miniſtery of true Paſtors, and Teachers is not the Miniſtery of Prieſts and Deacons.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch is the Miniſtery of our Aſſemblies. <hi>Ergo,</hi> and for the profe of the Aſſumption, I might ſend him back againe to my firſt Argument. But I wil leaue ſuch a kind of diſputing to himſelf, as his owne peculier, and proue it otherwiſe thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which in the maine and eſſentiall faculties, &amp; offices therof, is oppoſite to the maine, and eſſential faculties, functions &amp; offices of Prieſts, and Deacons is not the Miniſtery of Prieſts, and Deacons.</item>
                     <item>But ſuch is our Miniſtery.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is not the Miniſtery of Prieſts and Deacons.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is vndeniable.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption may bee proued thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which is oppoſite to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſſe, is oppoſite to the maine and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall faculties, functions and offices of Prieſts and Deacons.</item>
                     <item>Such is our Miniſtery.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is oppoſite to the maine and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall faculties of Prieſts and Deacons.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>I doe not ſee, which of theis Premiſes hee can with any colourable reaſon deny. I will therfore for beare to proceed further in this Argument: vntill I ſee what hee can ſay againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:51"/>
                  <head>The third Argument.</head>
                  <p>That Miniſtery which profeſſing Chriſt by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his covenant with the ſeales of it, doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and profeſſedly warre againſt the Beaſt and againſt all that worſhip his Image, and receave his marke in their forehead and hand, cannot without ſin bee ſeperated from.</p>
                  <p>Such is our Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>Therfore it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not without ſin be ſeperated from.</p>
                  <p>The Propoſition is true. For noe Miniſtery ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſt, but the true Miniſtery of Ieſus Chriſt, doth directly and profeſſedly warre in manner, &amp; forme aforeſaide.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption I proue thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which ſo profeſſing oppoſeth it ſelf profeſſedly to the Pope of Rome as that great Antichriſt, which directly and expreſly renounceth all Eccleſiaſticall homage vnto him, or any of his profeſſed cleargie, That denieth and diſputeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt (moſt effectually) all the maine and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points of Popery, which oppoſeth it ſelfe to the vttermoſt of the ſtrength and Power therof, to all the profeſſed frends of the Pope, and Church of Rome, That houldeth and maintaineth all the members therof to bee hereticks and Idolators, and in the ſtate of condemnation, and ſuch as no good Chriſtian ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate ſpiritually withall, That Miniſtery (I ſay) doth directly warre againſt the beaſt, and againſt al that worſhip his Image, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>But all this is donne in and by our Miniſtery.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:52"/>
                     <item>Therefore it doth directly, and profeſſedly warre againſt the Beaſt, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>I know not which of theis Propoſitions hee can with any face deny; but deny either when hee will, I ſhall bee readie to proue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fourth Argument.</head>
                  <p>That Miniſtery which, deriveth the power and functions therof from Chriſt cannot without ſinne bee ſeperated from.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Power and functions therof from Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it cannot without ſinne bee ſeperated from.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The profes of the maine propoſition of this fourth Argument will ſerue to proue this Propoſition.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is as ſufficiently proued by my third and firſt Argument as his contrary, is by his third and firſt. But I further proue it thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>If the Power and functions of our Miniſtery for the ſubſtance therof, bee the very ſame, for which Chriſt aſcended vp into Heaven to procure for the edification of his body the Church, then doth it for the ſubſtance therof, derive the Power and functions therof from Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>But the firſt is true, therfore the later is true alſo.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Conſequent of the Proproſition is vndeniable.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is as vndeniable, Except hee can ſhew any ſubſtantiall difference betweene the one and the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177068:52"/>
                  <head>The fift Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which worketh vpon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, by a true ſpirituall calling cannot without ſinne bee ſeperated from.</item>
                     <item>Such is our Miniſtery.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it cannot without ſinne bee ſeperated from.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition cannot bee gaine ſaid.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proued by my 2. Argument, but I further proue it in this manner.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which worketh vpon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men onely by a ſpirituall gift and grace giuen by Chriſt, and directed by the word of God, doth worke vpon the conſciences of men by a true Spirituall calling.</item>
                     <item>Theis doth the Miniſtery of our Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it worketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſciences of men by a true Spirituall calling.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The truth of either of theis Propoſitions, I ſhal eaſily proue, if they bee deinde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſixt Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies is noe ſtrang Miniſtery.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is a ſinne to ſeperate from it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>This Anticedent is better proued by my firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: then his contrary Aſſumption is by his firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I proue it not withſtanding thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which for the ſubſtance therof, was practized by Chriſt, the Apoſtles many worthy
<pb facs="tcp:177068:53"/>and famous Martyrs and witneſſes of Ieſus Chriſt in Church Aſſemblies is no ſtrange Miniſtery.</item>
                     <item>Such is our Miniſtery for the ſubſtance therof.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is no ſtrange Miniſtery.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Surely hee will never deny the Propoſition.</p>
                  <p>Nether can hee deny the Aſſumption, except he can ſhew a Subſtantiall difference, between the Miniſteries aforeſaide.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſeaventh Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which is from Heauen cannot without ſinne bee ſeperated from.</item>
                     <item>The Miniſtery of our Church Aſſemblies is from Heaven.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not without ſinne be ſeperated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is plaine.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption is proued by all the former Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which in his logick Scholes, in his owne cauſe is profe good enough. But I ad a further profe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>That Miniſtery which in all the parts and Power therof is principally excercized and directed, to bring men to Heaven is a Miniſtery from Heaven.</item>
                     <item>Such is our Miniſtery aforeſaid.</item>
                     <item>Therfore it is from Heaven.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition is firme. It being not poſſible, that that Miniſtery which is from Earth or hell ſhould bee principally directed and excercized in all the parts and Powers therof to bring men to Heaven.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſumption may not bee denied, except hee can ſhew in what other thing it is more principally excerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and to what other end, directed, which hee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:177068:53"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO CERTAINE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDES OFTEN PVBLISHED by M. Iohnſon, the deciding wherof (as hee ſaith) will end the controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and vs.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The firſt Demande.</head>
                  <p>WHether the Lord Ieſus Chriſt haue by his laſt will and Teſtament, given vnto and ſet in his Church, ſufficient ordinarie officers, with their calling, worke and maintenance: for the adminiſtration of his holy things, and for the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ordinarie inſtruction, guidance and ſervice of his Church, to the end of the worlde.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Anſwer directly (vnderſtanding by <hi>Officers,</hi> ſpirituall officers) that hee hath; And that it is a Sinne herein to breake his will and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ether by depriving the Church of any of thoſe officers, or by bringing into it any other
<pb facs="tcp:177068:54"/>kinde, with any other kinde of calling, or worke, then hee hath appointed in the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That not withſtanding this, the Civill Magiſtrate hath power, to ſet over the Churches of Chriſt in his Dominions, Commiſſioners and overſeers, which are not ſpecially appointed by Chriſt in his Teſtament, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy to guide &amp; gouerne the Churches, &amp; to maintaine thoſe priviledges, liberties, offices &amp; orders, that Chriſt hath endowed them with all, againſt all the enemies, both without and within the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Concerning the maintenaunce of the Miniſters: Chriſt hath ſet downe no more in his Teſtament, then this in effect, <hi>That the labourer is worthie of his hire:</hi> And that for their Miniſtration of Spirituall things, the Churches that enjoy their labours, ought to Miniſter to them, of their Temporals. But after what eſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they ſhall be maintained, he hath (for ought appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth yet to the contrary) ether left it to the diſcretion of the Churches, if they haue the free diſpoſition of their temporall goods in their owne hand: or of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, who in ſuch caſes may ſee what is fitter, then the Churches themſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether the Offices of Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons and Helpers, be thoſe offices appointed by Chriſt in his Teſtament before ſaid? Or whether the preſent eccleſiaſticall offices of Arch-Biſhops, Lord-Biſhops, Suffraganes, Deanes, Prebendaries, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Pettie Cannons, Prieſts, Deacons, Arch-Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:54"/>Doctors of Divinitie, Chaplins or Houſe-Prieſts, Commiſſaries, Officials, Proctors, Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, Vagrant or Mercenary, Preachers, Church-wardens, Sidemen, Clarkes, Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons. and the reſt now had in the Cathedrall and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhionall Aſſemblies, bee thoſe offices oppointed by Chriſt in his Teſtament, as is aforeſaid or no?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I graunt, that the Offices in the firſt place mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, are thoſe very offices which Chriſt hath appointed that there is no Church of Chriſt, but hath vſe and need of them; And that ſuch are ſomeway defective, that want any one of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That yet not withſtanding, they may bee true Churches, that want ſome of them; yea the chiefeſt of them, as thos Aſſemblies of our owne profeſſion in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, haue for many yeares (as I take it) bin without, ether all or chiefeſt of them; And yet they judge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues true Churches: yea, though they haue not ſo much as the Sacraments adminiſtred amongſt them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Where the Civill Magiſtrate doth his dutie as hee ought: and where the Churches haue the benifit of his help, for the ſuppreſſing of ſinne, and the relieving of the poor, and thoſe that are in any diſtres (which the Apoſtolicall Churches wanted) there the want of ſome of theis offices, may bee the better borne with all: and the Church leſſe defective, that doth want them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the two latter.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I graunt that none of thoſe offices here mentioned in the latter part (excepting that of Deacons,) are in name thoſe offices which Chriſt hath appointed: ſome of them, nether in name, nor in deed: ſome in deed,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:55"/>though not in name; Some haue the name of that, which indeed they are not; Some though they bee ſet over the Churches: Yet are not indeed any proper offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Church; Some offices here named nether in deed nor name, as they are ſuch, are eccleſiaſtical offices, but onely ſchoole Titles and dignities giuen to men eminent in learning, for incouragement of others to ſtudy good letters, eſpecially divinitie.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. All the offices appointed by Chriſt to bee in his Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the end of the world, in effect and ſubſtance may be found conteined vnder ſome of theis, though ſomwhat diſguiſed with ſtrange names, borrowed from the Church of Rome: and the principall &amp; moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, are vnder ſome of theis. For many of theis which you diſpitfully cal, mercenary Preachers, Prieſts, Houſe-Prieſts: yea, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, are in very deed and truth, in office &amp; practice (whatſoever they are in name) The very Paſtors and Teachers, that Chriſt hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, miniſtring in his Churches, according to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and callings: And thoſe gifts which Chriſt had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon them al, the ordinary meanes of ſalvation. As for theis varitie of names, moſt of them ariſe, from that varitie of maintenance that is in our Churches, and not of their ſpirituall offices; So that in this manner to diſpute againſt our Churches, becauſe the Miniſters therof, haue ſuch &amp; ſuch names, is: as though one ſhould diſpute againſt the Church of the Iewes in Chriſts time and haue denied communion with it, asking; whether Prieſts, Levites, and Prophets, were not thoſe officers which God had appointed to governe the Church of the Iewes with all? Or whether Scribes, Phariſies, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:55"/>Captaines of the Temple, Rulers of the Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, Doctors of the Law, Centurions, Souldiers, the high-Prieſts Servants, &amp;c. were thoſe Officers? Or as if one diſputing againſt your owne Churches, or thoſe which haue (though not ſo fully, as you would haue them) interteined the ſame diſcipline with you, ſhould: to warrant their ſeperation from you, &amp; their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of you as falſe Churches, move the very ſame queſtion in nature vnto you; Asking you whether Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons &amp; Helpers, be not thoſe Offices, which Chriſt hath appointed in his Teſtament: Or whether Schiſmaticks, Refractaries, lay-Aldermen; Pariſh Biſhops, Conſiſtorians, Pariſh Popes, Proctors of ſpitle houſes, Dawbers, Thackers, Tailers, Tinkers, &amp;c. be thoſe Officers? for thus it hath pleaſed ſome, to put theis odious names vpon thoſe, which bearre &amp; exerciſe the offices of Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The third Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether the callings and entrance into the eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall offices aforeſaid, their adminiſtration and maintenance, now had and retained in England, bee the manner of calling, adminiſtration and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which Chriſt hath appointed, for the Offices of the Church, aboue named, or no?</p>
                  <p>Not to ſtand (for the avoiding of multiplicity of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſarie queſtions) vpon defence of the calling, entran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, adminiſtration and maintenaunce of all; I aunſwer directly and plainly, That the Calling, entraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, adminiſtration and maintenance, of many
<pb facs="tcp:177068:56"/>(at the leaſt) that are called into eccleſiaſticall offices, is in very effect and ſubſtance the ſame, that Chriſt hath appointed. They are men inſtructed in the knowledge of good Letters, eſpecially in divinitie. They haue a gift in ſome good meaſure, to devide the word of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the neceſſities of the people, over whom they are ſet. They haue a deſire, to do Chriſt and his Church ſervice in his Miniſtrie, and a purpoſe to giue themſelues over vnto that worke. They haue in ſome good meaſure, (for none hath them in perfection) all thoſe graces and gifts that Paul to Timothie, requires to bee in Biſhops and Elders; They are ſo judged and eſteemed to bee of other Miniſters, and well grounded Chriſtians, and of thoſe people which ſubmit vnto their Miniſtrie, who accepting of them and their Miniſtrie as ſent of God, deſiring and yealding themſelues to liue vnder them, as is fitting for Chriſtians: And they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to guide and governe them, as becometh ſpirituall leaders and guides; Such calling and entraunce as this, haue many of our Church-officers; more then this in ſubſtance and effect, is not appointed by Chriſt. Thoſe defects and errors which over and beſides, many time; they yeald vnto in their calling, entraunce and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, are not of that nature and qualitie, that they make anullitie thereof, or make it a fals, and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian calling, entrance or adminiſtration. The mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance they liue by, as it is no where in ſpeciall appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Chriſt: ſo is it no where in generall, or ſpeciall forbidden; In the yealding wher-of vnto the Miniſters, they fulfill the Teſtament of Chriſt, in giving of their temporall things, for ſpirituall, in giving hire to the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:56"/>Labourers, &amp;c. and do not therin breake any parts els therof, hee having no where forbiden, any ſuch manner of maintenance, but left it indifferent, to giue money or fruits, In fruits to giue the twentith, the twelfth, the tenth, the eighth of the increaſe, according ether to their eſtate, or the neceſſitie of the Miniſters, wherein the Magiſtrate hath authority to rule and define, who hath in his hand, the power of mens temporall eſtates; or the Church, if the Magiſtrate leaue vnto them, the free vſe of their owne Temporalties; Nether is the tenth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be giuen by the Magiſtrate, or yealded to bee given by the Church, to the maintenaince of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, any more ceremoniall or Iudaicall, in regard of the number, then in regard of the matter; Nether did their any Miniſtery, lie ſo much in the quantity of the thing given, as in the very gift and offering it ſelfe; So that by the ſame reaſon, that you make it vnlawfull, for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be maintained by tithes, you make it vnlawfull for them, to haue any kinde of maintenaunce from the Church, there having bin a Ceremonie, in the very mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelf, as much as in the quantitie, or number. For not onely their giving the tithe of their increaſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the very giving of their increaſe it ſelfe, out of that conſideration, was ceremoniall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fourth Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether every true viſible Church of Chriſt, bee not a companie of people called and ſeperated out from the worlde, and the fals worſhip and waies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by the word of God: and joined together in the
<pb facs="tcp:177068:57"/>fellowſhip of the Goſpell, by voluntarie profeſſion of the faith, and obedience of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, 1. That every true viſible Church of Chriſt is ſuch a people.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That yet, not withſtanding they bee ſuch; they may in their infirmitie and ignorance, walke in ſome of the waies, and practice ſome parts of the fals worſhip of the world, not withſtanding their ſaid ſeperation, conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and profeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They may in time become, the true viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, which at the firſt were not, in the ſaid manner and forme, called, ſeperated and joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but forced and conſtrained againſt their will by the ſword of the Magiſtrate. 4. Many of thoſe Churches in our kingdome from which you ſeperate, as they now ſtand, are ſuch a companie of people, ſo called, ſeperated and joined together: though in all three, there may bee ſome kinde of defects and wants.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fift Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether the Sacraments, being the ſeales of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes which is by faith, may be adminiſtred vnto any other, but to the faithfull and their feed: or in any other Miniſtrie, or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner then is appointed by Ieſus Chriſt, the Apoſtle and high Prieſt of our profeſſion? And whether they be no otherwiſe adminiſtred, in our Cathedrall &amp; Pariſhionall Churches in England.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I graunt, that the Sacraments ought to bee admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, onely to the faithfull in outward profeſſion, and their ſeed, and in no other Miniſtrie, or manner, then is appointed by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:177068:57"/> 2. In many of our Churches (at the leaſt) they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in no other manner, from and by no other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, then Chriſt hath appointed: nor to no other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 3. Every error and defect, in ſome part of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and forme, and miniſtrie, a riſing of ignorance, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, maketh not the Churches fals Churches; except you hould, That no true perticuler Church can erre, which is a more groſſe opinion, then that of the Papiſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſixt Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether the booke of Common Praier, with the feaſts, faſts, holy daies, ſtinted Praiers &amp; liturgie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed therin, &amp; vſed in theis Aſſemblies, be the true worſhip of God, commaunded in his word: or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe &amp; invention of man, for Gods worſhip &amp; ſervice.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Though it ſhould bee graunted, that the booke of Common praier in all the parts and percels therof, is not the true worſhip of God, but containeth in it ſome deviſes and inventions of man; yet, the true worſhip of God (not withſtanding) is preſcribed in it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. So much of it as is vſed in many of our Churches, is the true worſhip of God, and in effect commanded in his word.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thoſe deviſes and inventions of men, with the feaſts, faſts &amp; holy daies therin preſcribed, though they ſhould be graunted, to be ſinnes and corruptions in our Churches, &amp; ſuch as ought not to be conformed vnto: &amp; ſuch as we ought rather to ſeperate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Churches then ether by ſubſcription, conformity, or any other meanes, to approue; yet are they not of that nature, that
<pb facs="tcp:177068:58"/>the ſimple vſe of any, or all of them, doth deſtroy the very being of thoſe Churches, which vſe them: making them fals Churches, and ſuch as wee may haue no ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall communion withall, no not in the beſt things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſeaventh Demande.</head>
                  <p>Whether all people and Churches without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be not bound in Religion onely, to receive and ſubmit vnto that Miniſtry, worſhip and order, which Chriſt as Lord and King, hath given and appointed to his Church? Or whether any may receiue &amp; joine vnto another deviſed by man, for the ſervice of God? And conſequently, whether they that joine to the preſent eccleſiaſticall Miniſtery, worſhip and order of the Cathedrall, and Pariſhionall Aſſemblies, can bee aſſured by the word of God, that they joine to the former ordained by Chriſt, and not to the latter deviſed by man, even the man of ſinne, for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I graunt that wee are bound in Religion, to do that which is ſpecified in the firſt part of your queſtion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To joine with our eccleaſiiaſticall Miniſtrie, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and orders (at leaſt in thoſe Aſſemblies, whether Cathedrall or other, when and where all things are not performed, according to the rigour of our lawes) is not to joine with a Miniſtrie and worſhip, deviſed by that man of ſinne: but (though not in all the ſpecialties and formalities therof) with ſuch a Miniſtrie and worſhip, as is required and inſtituted of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They which joine to the preſent eccleſiaſticall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie,
<pb facs="tcp:177068:58"/>worſhip and order of the Cathedral or Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Aſſemblies in thoſe things which are performed therein, according to the true intent and meaning of our lawes, though ſome things bee done not warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the word: yet they may bee aſſured by the word of God, that they joine to the ſubſtance of that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, worſhip and order, which Chriſt as Lord &amp; King, hath given and appointed to his Church; At leaſt they may bee as well aſſured therof by Gods word, as any that joine with the preſent eccleſiaſticall Miniſtery, worſhip and order of the Aſſemblies of thoſe of the Seperation, can bee aſſured by the ſame word, that they joine to that forme, which is ordained by Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
